<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>MRS FRANCES HARRIS'S PETITION.<lb/>  1700.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="AGendler 28JL04"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="# #spp-069-14W2-footnote-headnote-1"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="069-14W2">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">T<hi rend="small-caps">HIS</hi>, and the following piece of humour, which, in their own peculiar style, will probably never be equalled, were written while Swift was chaplain to Lord Berkeley in Ireland. None of his talents is more remarkable than the ease with which he could assume the character which he best pleased to occupy for the moment, and bind down his powerful genius to the thoughts, sentiments, and expressions of a chambermaid or housekeeper.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">T<hi rend="small-caps">O</hi> their Excellencies the Lords Justices of Ireland,<ref target="#spp-069-14W2-footnote-headnote-1">1</ref><note n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-footnote-headnote-1" place="foot">The Earls of Berkeley and of Galway.── H</note></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-14W2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">The humble petition of Frances Harris, <lb/> Who must starve and die a maid if it miscarries;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-1" n="1">Humbly sheweth, that I went to warm myself in Lady Betty's <note place="foot">·Lady Betty Berkeley, afterwards Germain.──H.</note> chamber, because I was cold;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-2" n="2">And I had in a purse seven pounds, four shillings, and sixpence, besides farthings, in money and gold;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-3" n="3">So because I had been buying things for my lady last night,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-4" n="4">I was resolved to tell my money, to see if it was right.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-5" n="5">Now, you must know, because my trunk has a very bad lock,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-6" n="6">Therefore all the money I have, which, God knows, is a very small stock,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-7" n="7">I keep in my pocket, tied about my middle, next my smock.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-8" n="8">So when I went to put up my purse, as God would have it, my smock was unripp'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-9" n="9">And instead of putting it into my pocket, down it slipp'd;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-10" n="10">Then the bell rung, and I went down to put my lady to bed;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-11" n="11">And, God knows, I thought my money was as safe as my maidenhead.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-12" n="12">So, when I came up again, I found my pocket feel very light;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-13" n="13">But when I search'd, and miss'd my purse, Lord! I thought I should have sunk outright.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-14" n="14">“Lord! madam,” says Mary, “how d'ye do?”── “Indeed, says I, “never worse:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-15" n="15">But pray, Mary, can you tell what I have done with my purse?”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-16" n="16">“Lord help me!” says Mary, “I never stirr'd out of this place!”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-17" n="17">“Nay,” said I, “I had it in Lady Betty's chamber, that's a plain case.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-18" n="18">So Mary got me to bed, and cover'd me up warm:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-19" n="19">However, she stole away my garters, that I might do myself no harm.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-20" n="20">So I tumbled and toss'd all night, as you may very well think,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-21" n="21">But hardly ever set my eyes together, or slept a wink.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-22" n="22">So I was a-dream'd, methought, that I went and search'd the folks round,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-23" n="23">And in a corner of Mrs Dukes's <note place="foot">·Wife to one of the footmen.── H.</note> box, tied in a rag, the money was found.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-24" n="24">So next morning we told Whittle,<note place="foot">·The Earl of Berkeley's valet.── H.</note> and he fell a swearing:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-25" n="25">Then my dame Wadgar <note place="foot">·The old deaf housekeeper.── H.</note> came, and she, you know, is thick of hearing.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-26" n="26">“Dame,” said I, as loud as I could bawl, “do you know what a loss I have had?”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-27" n="27">“Nay,” says she, “my Lord Colway's <note place="foot">·Galway.── H.</note> folks are all very sad:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-28" n="28">For my lord Dromedary <note place="foot">·The Earl of Drogheda, who, with the primate, was to succeed the two earls, then lords justices of Ireland.</note> comes a Tuesday without fail.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-29" n="29">“Pugh!” said I, “but that's not the business that I ail.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-30" n="30">Says Cary, <note place="foot">·Clerk of the kitchen.── H.</note> says he, “I have been a servant this five and twenty years come spring,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-31" n="31">And in all the places I lived I never heard of such a thing.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-32" n="32">“Yes,” says the steward, <note place="foot">·Ferris; whom the poet terms in his Journal a scoundrel dog.</note> “I remember when I was at my Lord Shrewsbury's,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-33" n="33">Such a thing as this happen'd, just about the time of <hi rend="italics">gooseberries</hi>.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-34" n="34">So I went to the party suspected, and I found her full of grief:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-35" n="35">(Now, you must know, of all things in the world I hate a thief:)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-36" n="36">However, I was resolved to bring the discourse slily about:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-37" n="37">“Mrs Dukes,” said I, “here's an ugly accident has happened out:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-38" n="38">'Tis not that I value the money three skips of a louse;<note place="foot">·A usual saying of hers.── H.</note></l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-39" n="39">But the thing I stand upon is the credit of the house.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-40" n="40">'Tis true, seven pounds, four shillings, and sixpence, makes a great hole in my wages:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-41" n="41">Besides, as they say, service is no inheritance in these ages.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-42" n="42">Now, Mrs Dukes, you know, and everybody understands,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-43" n="43">That though 'tis hard to judge, yet money can't go without hands.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-44" n="44">“The <hi rend="italics">devil</hi> take me!” said she, (blessing herself,) “if ever I saw't!”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-45" n="45">So she roar'd like a bedlam, as though I had call'd her all to naught.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-46" n="46">So, you know, what could I say to her any more?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-47" n="47">I e'en left her, and came away as wise as I was before.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-48" n="48">Well; but then they would have had me gone to the cunning man:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-49" n="49">“No,” said I, “'tis the same thing, the C<hi rend="small-caps">HAPLAIN</hi> will be here anon.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-50" n="50">So the Chaplain came in. Now the servants say he is my sweetheart,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-51" n="51">Because he's always in my chamber, and I always take his part.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-52" n="52">So, as the <hi rend="italics">devil</hi> would have it, before I was aware, out I blunder'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-53" n="53">“<hi rend="italics">Parson</hi>, said I, “can you cast a <hi rend="italics">nativity</hi>, when a body's plunder'd?”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-54" n="54">(Now you must know, he hates to be called <hi rend="italics">Parson</hi>, like the <hi rend="italics">devil!</hi>)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-55" n="55">“Truly,” says he, “Mrs Nab, it might become you to be more civil;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-56" n="56">If your money be gone, as a learned <hi rend="italics">Divine</hi> says, <note place="foot">·Dr Bolton, one of the chaplains.── F<hi rend="small-caps">AULKNER</hi>.</note> d'ye see,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-57" n="57">You are no <hi rend="italics">text</hi> for my handling; so take that from me:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-58" n="58">I was never taken for a <hi rend="italics">Conjurer</hi> before, I'd have you to know.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-59" n="59">“Lord!” said I, “don't be angry, I am sure I never thought you so;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-60" n="60">You know I honour the cloth; I design to be a Parson's wife;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-61" n="61">I never took one in <hi rend="italics">your coat</hi> for a conjurer in all my life.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-62" n="62">With that he twisted his girdle at me like a rope, as who should say,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-63" n="63">“Now you may go hang yourself for me!” and so went away.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-64" n="64">Well: I thought I should have swoon'd. “Lord!” said I, “what shall I do?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-65" n="65">I have lost my money, and shall lose my true love too!”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-66" n="66">Then my lord called me: “Harry,” <note place="foot">·A cant word of Lord and Lady Berkeley to Mrs Harris.── H.</note> said my lord, “don't cry;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-67" n="67">I'll give you something toward thy loss:” “And,” says my lady, “so will I.”</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-68" n="68">Oh! but, said I, what if, after all, the Chaplain won't come to?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-69" n="69">For that, he said, (an't please your Excellencies,) I must petition you.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-70" n="70">The premises tenderly considered, I desire your Excellencies' protection,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-71" n="71">And that I may have a share in next Sunday's collection;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-72" n="72">And, over and above, that I may have your Excellencies letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-73" n="73">With an order for the Chaplain aforesaid, or, instead of him, a better:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-74" n="74">And then your poor petitioner, both night and day,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-14W2-line-75" n="75">Or the Chaplain (for 'tis his <hi rend="italics">trade</hi>,) as in duty bound, shall ever <hi rend="italics">pray</hi>.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
