<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TO THEIR<lb/>  EXCELLENCIES<lb/>  THE<lb/>  <hi rend="italics">Lords Justices of</hi> I<hi rend="small-caps">RELAND</hi>,<lb/>  <hi rend="italics">The Humble Petition of</hi> Frances Harris,<lb/>  <hi rend="italics">Who must starve, &amp; die a Maid if it miscarries</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="AMP 29SE95"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="069-20X-">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Anno</hi> 1700.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-20X--headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-1" n="1"><hi rend="italics">Humbly Sheweth</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="display-initial">T</hi>Hat I went to warm my self in Lady <hi rend="italics">Betty's</hi> chamber, because I was cold,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-2" n="2">And I had in a Purse, seven Pound four Shillings and six Pence, besides farthings, in Money and Gold;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-3" n="3">So because I had been buying things for my Lady last night,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-4" n="4">I was resolved to tell my Money, to see if it was right:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-5" n="5">Now you know, because my Trunk has a very bad lock, 3}</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-6" n="6">Therefore all the Money I have, which, God knows, is a very small stock,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-7" n="7">I keep in my pocket ty'd about my middle, next my smock.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-8" n="8">So when I went to put up my Purse, as God would have it, my smock was unript,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-9" n="9">And, instead of putting it into my pocket, down it slipt:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-10" n="10">Then the Bell rung, and I went down to put my Lady to bed,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-11" n="11">And, God knows, I thought my Money was as safe as my Maidenhead.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-12" n="12">So when I came up again, I found my pocket feel very light,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-13" n="13">But when I search'd, and miss'd my Purse, Lord! I thought I should have sunk outright.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-14" n="14">Lord! Madam, says <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi>, how d'ye do? Indeed, says I, never worse.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-15" n="15">But pray, <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi>, can you tell what I have done with my Purse?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-16" n="16">Lord help me, said <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi>, I never stirr'd out of this place!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-17" n="17">Nay, said I, I had it in Lady <hi rend="italics">Betty</hi>'s chamber, that's a plain case.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-18" n="18">So <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> got me to bed, and cover'd me up warm,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-19" n="19">However she stole away my Garters, that I might do my self no harm.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-20" n="20">So I tumbl'd and toss'd all night, as you may very well think,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-21" n="21">But hardly ever set my eyes together, or slept a wink.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-22" n="22">So I was a-dream'd, methought, that we went and search'd the folks round,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-23" n="23">And in a corner of Mrs. <hi rend="italics">Dukes</hi>'s box, ty'd in a rag, the Money was found.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-24" n="24">So next morning we told <hi rend="italics">Whittle</hi>, and he fell a swearing;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-25" n="25">Then my Dame <hi rend="italics">Wadgar</hi> came, and she, you know, is thick of hearing;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-26" n="26"><hi rend="italics">Dame</hi>, said I, as loud as I could bawl, do you know what a loss I have had?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-27" n="27">Nay, said she, my Lord <note place="foot">·<hi rend="italics">Gallway</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italics">Collway</hi>'s folks are all very sad,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-28" n="28">For my Lord <note place="foot">·<hi rend="italics">Drogheda</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italics">Dromedary</hi> comes a tuesday without fail;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-29" n="29">Pugh! said I, but that's not the business that I ail.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-30" n="30">Says <hi rend="italics">Cary</hi>, says he, I have been a Servant this five and twenty years, come Spring,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-31" n="31">And in all the places I liv'd, I never heard of such a thing.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-32" n="32">Yes, says the Steward, I remember when I was at my Lady <hi rend="italics">Shrewsbury</hi>'s,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-33" n="33">Such a thing as this happen'd, just about the time of Goosberries.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-34" n="34">So I went to the party suspected, and I found her full of grief;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-35" n="35">(Now you must know, of all things in the world, I hate a Thief.)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-36" n="36">However, I was resolv'd to bring the discourse slily about:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-37" n="37">Mrs. <hi rend="italics">Dukes</hi>, said I, here's an ugly accident has happen'd out;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-38" n="38">'Tis not that I value the Money three skips of a Louse;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-39" n="39">But the thing I stand upon, is the credit of the House;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-40" n="40">'Tis true, seven Pounds, four Shillings, and six pence, makes a great hole in my Wages,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-41" n="41">Besides, as they say, Service is no inheritance in these Ages.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-42" n="42">Now, Mrs. <hi rend="italics">Dukes</hi>, you know, and every body unsterstands,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-43" n="43">That tho' 'tis hard to judge, yet money can't go without hands.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-44" n="44">The Devil take me, said she, (blessing her self) if I ever saw't!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-45" n="45">So she roar'd like a Beldam, as tho' I had call'd her all to naught?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-46" n="46">So, you know, what could I say to her any more,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-47" n="47">I e'en left her, and came away as wise as I was before.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-48" n="48">Well: But then they would have had me gone to the Cunning Man;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-49" n="49">No, said I, 'tis the same thing, the Chaplain will be here anon.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-50" n="50">So the Chaplain came in; now the Servants say, he is my Sweet-heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-51" n="51">Because he's always in my Chamber, and I always take his part;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-52" n="52">So, as the Devil would have it, before I was aware, out I blunder'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-53" n="53">Parson, said I, can you cast a Nativity, when a Body's plunder'd?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-54" n="54">(Now you must know, he hates to be call'd Parson, like the Devil.)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-55" n="55">Truly, says he, Mrs. <hi rend="italics">Nab</hi>, it might become you to be more civil:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-56" n="56">If your Money be gone, as a learned Divine says, d'ye see,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-57" n="57">You are no Text for my handling, so take that from me:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-58" n="58">I was never taken for a Conjurer before, I'd have you to know.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-59" n="59">Lord, said I, don't be angry; I am sure I never thought you so;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-60" n="60">You know, I honour the Cloth, I design to be a Parson's Wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-61" n="61">I never took one in your coat for a Conjurer in all my life.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-62" n="62">With that, he twisted his Girdle at me like a rope, as who should say,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-63" n="63">Now you may go hang your self for me, and so went away.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-64" n="64">Well, I thought I should have swoon'd; Lord, said I, what shall I do?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-65" n="65">I have lost my Money, and shall lose my True-Love too.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-66" n="66">Then my Lord call'd me; <hi rend="italics">Harry</hi>, said my Lord, don't cry,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-67" n="67">I'll give something towards thy loss; and says my Lady, so will I.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-68" n="68">Oh but, said I, what if after all my Chaplain won't come to?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-69" n="69">For that, he said (an't please your Excellencies) I must petition you.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-70" n="70"><lb/>The Premises tenderly consider'd, I desire your Excellencies Protection,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-71" n="71">And that I may have a share in next Sunday's Collection:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-72" n="72">And over and above, that I may have your Excellencies Letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-73" n="73">With an Order for the Chaplain aforesaid; or, instead of him, a better:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-74" n="74">And then your poor Petitioner, both night and day,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-20X--line-75" n="75">Or the Chaplain (for 'tis his trade) as in Duty bound, shall ever Pray.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
