<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>To Their Excellencies &amp;.c.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="JW 14NO02"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>√'d JW 15NO02; √'d JW 24JE03 in situ and tochk items resolved; √'d JW 28AU09 agt film; ed. JW 18AP04, 1JL07, 9OC14, 6JE16, 11OC16 (and remark); tochk item JW 24JA07 and resolved JW 28AU09</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="069-651B">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><lb/><lb/>The Humble Petition of Frances Harris, <lb/> who must starve, and Dy a Maid if it Miscarries.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">see page 258</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-651B-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">Sept: 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1708.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l rend="indent(2)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-1" n="1">|Humbly sheweth.<lb/>_|That I went to warm my self in Lady Betty's Chamber, because I was Cold</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-2" n="2">And I had in a purse 7<hi rend="superscript">ḷ</hi> 8<hi rend="superscript">ṣ</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">ḍ</hi> (beside Farthings) in Mony and Gold.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-3" n="3">So because I had been buying Things for my Lady last Night</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-4" n="4">I was Resolv'd to tell my Mony to see if it was Right.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-5" n="5">Now you must know because my Trunk has a uery Bad Lock 3}</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-6" n="6">Therfore all the Mony I have which <hi rend="underlined">Alas</hi>, is a uery small Stock</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-7" n="7">I keep in a Pocket ty'd about my Middle next my Smock</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-8" n="8">So when I put up my purse as <hi rend="underlined">ill luck</hi> wou'd have it, my Shift was unripp'd</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-9" n="9">And instead of putting it into my Pocket down it slipt</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-10" n="10">Then the Bell rung and I went down to put my Lady to Bed</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-11" n="11">When I <hi rend="underlined">verily</hi> thought my Mony was as Safe as my Maiden-Head.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-12" n="12">So when I came up agen, I found my Pocket very light</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-13" n="13">But when I search'd and Missed my Purse, I thought I shou'd ha' sunk outright.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-14" n="14">Lord Madam says Mary, How Do you doe? Indeed says I neuer worse</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-15" n="15">But pray Mary Can you tell what I have Done with my Purse.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-16" n="16">Lord help me said Mary I neuer stirr'd out of this Place.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-17" n="17">Nay said I, I had it in Lady Betty's Chamber that's a Plain Case.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-18" n="18">So Mary gott me to Bed and Cover'd me up warm</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-19" n="19">Howeuer she stole away my Garters, That I might Do my self no Harm.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-20" n="20">So I tumbl'd and toss'd all the Night, as you may very well think</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-21" n="21">But hardly euer set my Eies togather, or slept a wink.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-22" n="22">So I was Dream'd methought, that we went and search'd y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> folks round</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-23" n="23">And in a Corner of M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Duke's Box, ty'd in a Rag, the Mony was Found.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-24" n="24">So next Morning wee told Whittle, and He fell a Swearing;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-25" n="25">Than M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wadgar Comes, and She you must know is Thick of Hearing.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-26" n="26">Dame said I as loud as I Cou'd Bawl, do y<hi rend="superscript">u</hi> know w<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> a loss I have had,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-27" n="27">Nay, said she my L<hi rend="superscript">ḍ</hi> <note place="foot">·Ld: Galloway.</note> <hi rend="underlined">Colway</hi>'s Folks are all uery Sad──</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-28" n="28">For my Lord <note place="foot">·Ld: Drogheda.</note> <hi rend="underlined">Dromedary</hi> Comes a Tusday without Fail──</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-29" n="29">Puh said I, but thats not the Business I ail.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-30" n="30">Says Cary, says He, I have been a Serv<hi rend="superscript">ṭ</hi> this 5. an 20 years Come Spring</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-31" n="31">And in all the Places I liv'd, I neuer heard of such a Thing.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-32" n="32">Yes, says the Steward when I was at my Lady Shrewsbury's</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-33" n="33">Such a Thing as this happen'd, just about the time of Goosburys.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-34" n="34">So I went to the Party suspected, and found her full of greif.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-35" n="35">Now you must know of all Things in the World, I hate a Theif.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-36" n="36">However I was resolu'd to bring the Discourse Slily about</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-37" n="37">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Duke's said I, here's an Vgly Accident happen'd out;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-38" n="38">'Tis not that I value the Mony three Skips of a Lowse,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-39" n="39">But the Thing I stand upon is the Credit of the Howse.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-40" n="40">'Tis true 7<hi rend="superscript">ḷ</hi> an 4<hi rend="superscript">ṣ</hi> an 6<hi rend="superscript">ḍ</hi> makes a great Hole in my Wages</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-41" n="41">Besides as they say, service is no Inheritance in these Ages;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-42" n="42">Now M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>:  Dukes you know and every Body Vnderstands</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-43" n="43">That tho' 'tis hard to judg── Mony Can't go without Hands.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-44" n="44">The Devil take me said she (Blessing herself) if I euer saw't</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-45" n="45">So she roar'd like a Bedlam, as tho'f I had Call'd Her to Naught.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-46" n="46">So, you know what cou'd I say to her any more</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-47" n="47">I e'en left her; and came away as wise as I was before.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-48" n="48">Well; but then they wou'd have had me gone to the Cunning Man</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-49" n="49">No said I tis the same Thing, The Chaplain will be here anon.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-50" n="50">So the Chaplain Came in, Now the Servants say, He is my Sweet-Heart</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-51" n="51">Because hee's alwaies in my Chamber, and I alwaies take his part.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-52" n="52">So, as the Devil wou'd haue it, before I was aware, out I blunder'd</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-53" n="53">Parson said I, can you Cast a Nativity when a Body's Plunder'd.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-54" n="54">Now you must know, He hates to be Call'd Parson like y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> Devil;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-55" n="55">Truly said he, M<hi rend="superscript">rṣ</hi> Nab; it might become you to be more Civill.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-56" n="56">If your Mony be gone; As a Learned Divine say's d'ye see</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-57" n="57">You are no Text for my handling, take that from mee.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-58" n="58">I was neuer taken for a Conjuror before, I'd haue you to know</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-59" n="59">Lord said I, don't be Angry, I'm sure I never Thought you So.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-60" n="60">You know I honour the Cloath; I design to be a Parsons Wife;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-61" n="61">I neuer took one in your Coat, for a Conjurer in all my Life.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-62" n="62">With that He Twisted his Girdle like a Rope, as who shou'd say</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-63" n="63">Now you may go Hang your self for me, and so went away.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-64" n="64">Well, I thought I shou'd have Swoon'd, Lord said I, what shall I Do?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-65" n="65">I've lost my Mony, and I shall loose my True-Love too.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-66" n="66">Then my Lord Call'd me, Harris said my Lord, don't Cry</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-67" n="67">I'le give somthing toward thy loss, and says my Lady so will I.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-68" n="68">Oh but said I, what if after all, my Chaplain won't come too</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-69" n="69">For that He said, (an't please your Excellencys) I must Petition you.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-70" n="70"><lb/>The Premisses tenderly Consider'd, I desire y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Excellencys Protection</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-71" n="71">And that I may haue a share in Next Sundays Collection.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-72" n="72">And ouer and aboue, that I may haue your Excellencys Letter</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-73" n="73">With an Order for the Chaplain aforesaid, or (instead of Him) a Better.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-74" n="74">And then your Poor Petitioner both Night and Day,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-651B-line-75" n="75">Or the Chaplain (for 'tis His Trade) as in Duty Bound shall euer pray.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
