<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="JR 21JA97"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>√'d JW 24JA97 agt 11L-; cleaned and query JIF 1AP98; cleaned and query JIF 8MY98; queried spots corrected JW 17JE98; date corrected JW 7MR01; ed. JW 5NO16</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="136-10TA">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">──────<hi rend="italics">Poetica surgit<lb/>Tempestas</hi>.──────Juv.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">S</hi>TORMS at Sea are so frequently described by the ancient Poets, and copied by the Moderns, that whenever I find the Winds begin to rise in a new Heroick Poem, I generally skip a Leaf or two till I come into Fair Weather. <hi rend="italics">Virgil</hi>'s <hi rend="italics">Tempest</hi> is a Master-piece in this Kind, and is indeed so naturally drawn, that one who has made a Voyage can scarce read it without being Sea-sick.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">Land Showers are no less frequent among the Poets than the former: But I remember none of them which have not fallen in the Country; for which Reason they are generally filled with the Lowings of Oxen, and the Bleatings of Sheep, and very often embellished with a Rainbow.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-4">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-136-10TA-headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Virgil</hi>'s <hi rend="italics">Land Shower</hi> is likewise the best in its Kind: It is indeed a Shower of Consequence, and contributes to the main Design of the Poem, by cutting off a tedious Ceremonial, and bringing Matters to a speedy Conclusion between Two Potentates of different Sexes. My ingenious Kinsman Mr. <hi rend="italics">Humphrey Wagstaff</hi>, who treats of every Subject after a Manner that no other Author has done, and better than any other can do, has sent me the Description of a City Shower. I do not question but the Reader remembers my Cousin's Description of the Morning as it breaks in Town, which is printed in the <hi rend="italics">9</hi>th <hi rend="italics">Tatler</hi>, and is another exquisite Piece of this local Poetry.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-1" n="1">Careful Observers may foretel the Hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-2" n="2">(By sure Prognosticks) when to dread a Shower:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-3" n="3">While Rain depends, the pensive Cat gives o'er</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-4" n="4">Her Frolicks, and pursues her Tail no more.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-5" n="5">Returning Home at Night, you'll find the Sink</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-6" n="6">Strike your offended Sense with double Stink;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-7" n="7">If you be wise, then go not far to dine,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-8" n="8">You'll spend in Coach-Hire more than save in Wine.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-9" n="9">A coming Shower your shooting Corns presage,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-10" n="10">Old Aches throb, your hollow Tooth will rage.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-11" n="11">Sauntring in Coffee-house is <hi rend="italics">Dulman</hi> seen,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-12" n="12">He damns the Climate, and complains of Spleen.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-13" n="13"><lb/>Mean while the <hi rend="italics">South</hi> rising with dabbled Wings,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-14" n="14">A sable Cloud athwart the Welkin flings,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-15" n="15">That swill'd more Liquor than it could contain,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-16" n="16">And, like a Drunkard, gives it up again.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-17" n="17">Brisk <hi rend="italics">Susan</hi> whips her Linen from the Rope,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-18" n="18">While the first drizz'ling Shower is born aslope:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-19" n="19">Such is that sprinkling which some careless Quean</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-20" n="20">Flirts on you from her Mop, but not so clean:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-21" n="21">You fly, invoke the Gods, then turning, stop</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-22" n="22">To rail; she singing, still whirls on her Mop.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-23" n="23">Not yet the Dust had shun'd th' unequal Strife,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-24" n="24">But, aided by the Wind, fought still for Life;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-25" n="25">And wafted with its Foe, by violent Gust,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-26" n="26">'Twas doubtful which was Rain, and which was Dust.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-27" n="27">Ah! Where must needy Poet seek for Aid,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-28" n="28">When Dust and Rain at once his Coat invade;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-29" n="29">His only Coat, where Dust confused with Rain,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-30" n="30">Roughen the Nap, and leave a mingled Stain.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-31" n="31"><lb/>Now in contiguous Drops the Flood comes down,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-32" n="32">Threat'ning with Deluge this <hi rend="italics">Devoted</hi> Town:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-33" n="33">To Shops in Crowds the daggled Females fly,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-34" n="34">Pretend to cheapen Goods, but nothing buy.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-35" n="35">The Templer spruce, while every Spout's a-broach,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-36" n="36">Stays till 'tis fair, yet seems to call a Coach:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-37" n="37">The tuck'd-up Sempstress walks with hasty Strides,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-38" n="38">While Streams run down her oil'd Umbrella's Sides.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-39" n="39">Here various Kinds, by various Fortunes led,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-40" n="40">Commence Acquaintance underneath a Shed,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-41" n="41">Triumphant Tories, and desponding Whigs,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-42" n="42">Forget their Feuds, and join to save their Wigs:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-43" n="43">Box'd in a Chair the Beau impatient sits,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-44" n="44">While Spouts run clatt'ring o'er the Roof by Fits,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-45" n="45">And ever and anon with frightful Din</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-46" n="46">The Leather sounds, he trembles from within.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-47" n="47">So when <hi rend="italics">Troy</hi> Chair-men bore the Wooden Steed,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-48" n="48">Pregnant with <hi rend="italics">Greeks</hi>, impatient to be freed,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-49" n="49">(Those Bully <hi rend="italics">Greeks</hi>, who, as the Moderns do,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-50" n="50">Instead of paying Chair-men, run them thro')</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-51" n="51"><hi rend="italics">Laoco'n</hi> struck the Outside with his Spear,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-52" n="52">And each imprison'd Hero quak'd for Fear.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-53" n="53"><lb/>Now from all Parts the swelling Kennels flow,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-54" n="54">And bear their Trophies with them as they go:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-55" n="55">Filth of all Hues and Odors seem to tell</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-56" n="56">What Street they sail'd from, by their Sight and Smell.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-57" n="57">They, as each Torrent drives, with rapid Force</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-58" n="58">From <hi rend="italics">Smithfield</hi> or <hi rend="italics">St. 'Pulchre</hi>'s shape their Course,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-59" n="59">And in huge Confluent join'd at <hi rend="italics">Snow-Hill</hi> Ridge,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-60" n="60">Fall from the <hi rend="italics">Conduit</hi> prone to <hi rend="italics">Holborn-Bridge</hi>.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-61" n="61">Sweepings from Butchers Stalls, Dung, Guts and Blood, 3}</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-62" n="62">Drown'd Puppies, stinking Sprats, all drench'd in Mud,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-136-10TA-line-63" n="63">Dead Cats and Turnep-Tops come tumbling down the Flood.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
