<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>THE LAWYER.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="SK 26JL08"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>ed. JW 16OC17</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="432B00233YD">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">ORIGINAL POETRY.&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">UNPUBLISHED POEM, BY DEAN SWIFT.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">To the Editor of the Dublin Literary Gazette</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-4">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1">
                <note rend="flush right">Limerick, April, 1830.</note>
              </l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="5" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-5">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-5-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-5-line-group-1-line-1">S<hi rend="small-caps">IR</hi>──I send you an extract from an unpublished poem, by Dean Swift, now in my possession. I was placed in my hands by a lady who resides in the County of Clare; and had been discovered amongst the papers of the late Bishop Bernard, of this city, whose intimacy with the great satirist is well known. It bears the Dean's own signature, and from the date (September 7th, 1728) which he has prefixed, (as he was in the habit of doing to many of his light pieces,) I conclude that it was written when Swift was residing at Market Hill, (the seat of Sir Arthur Acheson.) His letters, and the journal to Stella, contain several allusions corroboratory of the genuineness of the poem, as will appear from a perusal of the few notes I have subjoined to the extract. The little piece may not be thought in his best vein, yet it bears the stamp of his spirit in a sufficient degree to make what is called the <hi rend="italics">internal evidence</hi> of its paternity abundantly conclusive, and the irony in part is exquisitely subdued. It appears to have been written with the view of dissuading his friend Lindsay from embracing the legal profesion; and the extract which I give presents a sketch which is graphic at least; although the portrait is viewed through a mischief-making medium. He is banteringly defending the cause of the profession against those who say that the lawyer's money is easily earned, and lends his satire (like Mrs. Candour's scandal) the veil of charity. I preserve exactly the spelling and punctuation as they are in the original:──</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="6" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-6">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-6-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-6-line-group-1-line-1">In the conclusion of the poem, (which, even in the sketch just given, presents some touches of that shade of sober irony which has immortalized the Academy of Lagoda,) the Dean grows personal; and concludes with a joke at his old acquaintances, Carter (the Master of the Rolls,) Richard Tighe, and Connolly, to whom Lord Wharton was charged with having sold the place of a Privy Councillor, and Commissioner of the Revenue, and who was afterwards Speaker of the Irish House of Commons, and a Lord Justice. Robert Lindsay, to whom the poem is addressed, (and whose name it bears in the title,) is often mentioned with affectionate regard in the Dean's works; and is, I believe, the same to whom, in the will of Esther Vanhomrigh, we find the sum of £25 bequeathed, to buy a ring.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="7" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-7">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-7-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-7-line-group-1-line-1">I will add, Sir, that I feel a great satisfaction in being able to forward so valuable a contribution to the Dublin Literary Gazette──being the first attempt made for a long time to revive what that brilliant writer immortalized──the local literature of Ireland.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="8" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-8">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-8-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-8-line-group-1-line-1">I am, Sir, your obedient servant,</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="9" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-9">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-9-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-432B00233YD-headnote-9-line-group-1-line-1">
                <note rend="flush right">T<hi rend="small-caps">HE</hi> A<hi rend="small-caps">UTHOR OF THE </hi>C<hi rend="small-caps">OLLEGIANS</hi>.</note>
              </l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1"/>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
