<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="italics">Mary the Cook-Maid's Letter to Dr Sheridan</hi>
        </title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="985-ROGP">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-985-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-1" n="1">Well; if ever I saw such another man since my mother bound my head,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-2" n="2">You a gentleman! marry come up, I wonder where you were bred?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-3" n="3">I am sure such words does not become a man of your cloth,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-4" n="4">I would not give such language to a dog, faith and troth.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-5" n="5">Yes; you called my master a knave; fie Mr Sheridan, 'tis a shame</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-6" n="6">For a parson, who should know better things, to come out with such a name.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-7" n="7">Knave in your teeth, Mr Sheridan, 'tis both a shame and a sin,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-8" n="8">And the Dean my master is an honester man than you and all your kin:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-9" n="9">He has more goodness in his little finger, than you have in your whole body,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-10" n="10">My master is a parsonable man, and not a spindle-shanked hoddy-doddy.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-11" n="11">And now whereby I find you would fain make an excuse,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-12" n="12">Because my master one day, in anger, called you goose.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-13" n="13">Which, and I am sure I have been his servant four years since October,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-14" n="14">And he never called me worse than `sweetheart', drunk or sober:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-15" n="15">Not that I know his Reverence was ever concerned to my knowledge,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-16" n="16">Though you and your come-rogues keep him out so late in your wicked college.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-17" n="17"><lb/>You say you will eat grass on his grave: a Christian eat grass!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-18" n="18">Whereby you now confess yourself to be a goose or an ass:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-19" n="19">But that's as much as to say, that my master should die before ye;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-20" n="20">Well, well, that's as God pleases, and I don't believe that's a true story,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-21" n="21">om.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-22" n="22">om.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-23" n="23">And so say I told you so, and you may go tell my master; what care I?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-24" n="24">And I don't care who knows it, 'tis all one to Mary.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-25" n="25">Everybody knows, that I love to tell truth, and shame the devil;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-26" n="26">I am but a poor servant, but I think gentlefolks should be civil.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-27" n="27">Besides, you found fault with our victuals one day that you was here,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-28" n="28">I remember it was upon a Tuesday, of all days in the year.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-29" n="29">And Saunders the man says, you are always jesting and mocking,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-30" n="30">`Mary' said he, (one day, as I was mending my master's stocking,)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-31" n="31">`My master is so fond of that minister that keeps the school;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-32" n="32">I thought my master a wise man, but that man makes him a fool.'</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-33" n="33">`Saunders' said I, `I would rather than a quart of ale,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-34" n="34">He would come into our kitchen, and I would pin a dishclout to his tail.'</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-35" n="35">And now I must go, and get Saunders to direct this letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-36" n="36">For I write but a sad scrawl, but sister Marget she writes better.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-37" n="37">Well, but I must run and make the bed before my master comes from prayers,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-38" n="38">And see now, it strikes ten, and I hear him coming upstairs:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-39" n="39">Whereof I could say more to your verses, if I could write written hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-40" n="40">And so I remain in a civil way, your servant to command,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-985-ROGP-line-41" n="41">«FL»MARY.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
