<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A MODEST<lb/>  DEFENCE<lb/>  OF<lb/>  THE LADY'S DRESSING-ROOM.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="NSweeney 7FE10"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="P01072H1">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">A</hi> POEM, or Pamphlet, published in this kingdom without a name, will not long want one, if the paper maketh any noise.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">There is a certain person of distinction among us, who is conjectured to have written many things, both in prose and verse, for the service of the nation, which undoubtedly were published with his own consent. It is also believed, that he hath composed others occasionally for the amusement of himself and a few intimate friends; which, by the indiscretion of others, were, from stolen and uncorrected copies, <hi rend="italics">dragged into light</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">But I hold it for certain, that a much greater number have, by the boldness of Printers, and the want of judgement in Readers, been charged upon that Author, wherein he never had the smallest finger, as I am assured he hath often declared; and, which is remarkable, was as free in disowning some writings charged upon him, of which he had no reason to be ashamed, as he could be of the meanest productions of <hi rend="italics">Hibernian</hi> Grubstreet.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-4">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1">As to those <hi rend="italics">fatal Verses</hi>, called the Lady's Dressing Room, which have so highly inflamed the whole sex (except a very few of better judgement), as I can by no means justify the vulgar opinion, that seemeth to fix it upon a person so well known for works of a very different nature; so I cannot but lament the prevailing ill taste among us, which is not able to discover that useful satire running through every line; and the matter is as decently wrapped up as it is possible the subject could bear.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="5" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-5">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-5-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-5-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Cleanliness</hi> hath, in all polite ages and nations, been esteemed the chief corporal perfection in Women; as it is well known to those who are conversant with the ancient Poets. And so it is still among the young people of judgement and sobriety, when they are disposed to marry. And I do not doubt but that there is a great number of young ladies in this town and kingdom, who, in reading that Poem, find great complacency in their own minds, from a consciousness, that the satirical part in the Lady's Dressing-Room doth not in the least affect them.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="6" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-6">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-6-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-6-line-group-1-line-1">Wherefore it is manifest, that no Poem was ever written with a better design for the service of the <hi rend="italics">sex</hi>: wherein our Author hath observed, to a tittle, the precepts of his Master <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>; or, indeed, rather hath gone very far beyond him in the article of <hi rend="italics">decency</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="7" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-7">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-7-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-7-line-group-1-line-1">That great poet, instructing us what actions are fittest to be produced only upon the Scene, and which are most proper to be only related to the Audience, goeth many lengths beyond the Author of the Lady's Dressing-Room; for at the same instant when he sayeth some actions should not appear as done upon the stage, he allows they may be <hi rend="italics">recited</hi> with the pleasure and <hi rend="italics">elegance</hi>; and yet, when he cometh to particulars, his recital is extremely gross, and so are his very <hi rend="italics">precepts</hi> which forbid the actions: that, if our infinitely more modest Author had imitated his Master's <hi rend="italics">style</hi>, the whole world might, with great appearance of reason, have been up in arms against him.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="8" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-8">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-8-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-8-line-group-1-line-1">Therefore, to set these two Poets in a true light, I have ventured, for the satisfaction of both sexes, to translate, as literally as I could, ten lines in <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, upon the very subject, which our Author hath handled with a decency so far superior to his <hi rend="italics">Roman</hi> Master.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="9" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-9">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-9-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-9-line-group-1-line-1">To justify the truth of my translation, I desire all fine Gentlemen and Ladies will appeal from me to the information of the Learned, that I may be wholly clear from the last censure of misrepresenting so great an authority; for, indeed, if I have been guilty of any fault, it is in palliating the gross expressions in the original, and softening them very much to the <hi rend="italics">politeness</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">present age</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="10" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-10">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-10-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-10-line-group-1-line-1">The <hi rend="italics">Latin</hi> is word for word as follows:</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="11" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-11">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-11-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-11-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Aut agitur res in scenis, aut acta refertur. <lb/> Segniùs irritant animos demissa per aurem, <lb/> Quam qu/ae/ sunt oculis subjecta fidelibus, &amp; qu/ae/ <lb/> Ipse sibi tradit spectator. Non tamen intus <lb/> Digna geri, promes in scenam; multaque tolles <lb/> Ex oculis, qu/ae/ mox narret facundia pr/ae/sens. <lb/> Nec pueros coram populo Medea trucidet; <lb/> Aut humana palàm coquat exta nefarius Atreus; <lb/> Aut in avem Progne vertatur, Cadmus in anguem. <lb/> Quodcunque ostendis mihi sic, incredulus odi</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="12" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-12">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-12-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-12-line-group-1-line-1">The literal translation whereof is thus:</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="13" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-13">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-13-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-13-line-group-1-line-1">I desire the Reader will compare the most exceptionable lines in the Lady's Dressing-Room with the least offensive of those in <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>; although purged by me as much as could consist with preserving the true sense of the original. Yet this was the great master of politeness in the <hi rend="italics">Roman</hi> Empire, at the time it flourished most in arts and arms.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="14" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-14">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-14-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-14-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, you see, maketh use of the plain slovenly words, which our decent <hi rend="italics">Irish</hi> Poet industriously avoideth, and skippeth over a hundred dirty places without fouling his shoes. <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, on the contrary, plainly calleth a <hi rend="italics">spade</hi> a <hi rend="italics">spade</hi>, when there was not the least necessity; and when, with equal ease, as well as significancy, he might have expressed his meaning in homely terms, fit for the nicest ears of a queen or a dutchess.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="15" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-15">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-15-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01072H1-headnote-15-line-group-1-line-1">I do, therefore, positively decide in favour of our <hi rend="italics">Hibernian</hi> bard, upon the article of <hi rend="italics">decency</hi>; and am ready to defend my proposition against all mankind; that in the ten lines of <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, here faithfully and favourably translated, there are ten times more <hi rend="italics">slovenly expressions</hi>, than in the whole poem called the Lady's Dressing-Room; and for the truth of this proposition, I am ready to appeal to all the young ladies of the kingdom, or to such a <hi rend="italics">committee</hi> as my very adversaries shall appoint.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-1" n="1">S<hi rend="small-caps">OME</hi> Ladies <hi rend="italics">do their need</hi> before your face;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-2" n="2">Some only tell the <hi rend="italics">action</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">place</hi>.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-3" n="3">Our mind is less provok'd by what it hears,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-4" n="4">Than when the fact before our eyes appears.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-5" n="5">In closet dark, your <hi rend="italics">cedar-box</hi> be hid,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-6" n="6">Not in a parlour shewn without the lid.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-7" n="7">Some <hi rend="italics">actions</hi> must be always out of sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-8" n="8">Yet <hi rend="italics">elegantly told</hi> may give delight.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-9" n="9">Nurse must not hold the child, and cry, <hi rend="italics">Ee Hee</hi>!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-10" n="10">When madam and her friends are o'er their tea.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-11" n="11"><hi rend="italics">Atreus</hi>, with ladies by, mistake his wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-12" n="12">In new-born t────s to run a red-hot spit.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-13" n="13">Miss <hi rend="italics">Progne</hi> must not cry, <hi rend="italics">A Bird, a Bird</hi>!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-14" n="14">Before good company, and shew a t────d.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-15" n="15"><hi rend="italics">Cadmus</hi>, who voids out worms of monstrous size,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-16" n="16">In more good-manners should deceive our eyes;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-17" n="17">Must do his dirty work behind the scene,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-18" n="18">And, ere he shews the <hi rend="italics">vermin</hi>, wipe them clean.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-19" n="19">To bring such odious objects full in view,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01072H1-line-20" n="20">Though <hi rend="italics">fools</hi> may laugh, will make a <hi rend="italics">wise man</hi> spew.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
