<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="spp-P01008G1-title-1">A modest D<hi rend="small-caps">EFENCE</hi> of a late P<hi rend="small-caps">OEM</hi> by an unknown<lb/>  author, called, T<hi rend="small-caps">HE </hi>L<hi rend="small-caps">ADY'S </hi>D<hi rend="small-caps">RESSING</hi>-<lb/>  R<hi rend="small-caps">OOM</hi> <ref target="#spp-P01008G1-footnote-title-1">1</ref><note n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-footnote-title-1" place="foot">See this poem in vol. 6. p. 341</note>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="SGough 5AP07"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-P01008G1-footnote-title-1 #spp-P01008G1-title-1"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="P01008G1">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">Written in the year 1732.&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">[<hi rend="italics">The poem on the</hi> Lady's dressing-room <hi rend="italics">having given offence to a few</hi> squeamish ladies, <hi rend="italics">and some</hi> fine gentlemen, <hi rend="italics">it was thought proper to publish the following</hi> defence.]</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">A</hi> Poem, or pamphlet, published in this kingdom without a name, will not long want one, if the paper maketh any noise.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-4">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1">There is a certain <hi rend="italics">person</hi> of distinction among us, who is conjectured to have written many things, both in prose and verse, for the service of the nation, which undoubtedly were published with his own consent. It is also believed, that he has composed others occasionally, for the amusement of himself and a few intimate friends; which, by the indiscretion of others, were, from stolen and incorrect copies, <hi rend="italics">dragged into light</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="5" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-5">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-5-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-5-line-group-1-line-1">But I hold it for certain, that a much greater number have, by the boldness of <hi rend="italics">printers</hi>, and the want of judgment in <hi rend="italics">readers</hi>, being charged upon that <hi rend="italics">author</hi>, wherein he never had the smallest finger, as I am assured he hath often declared; and, which is remarkable, was as free in disowning some writings charged upon him, of which he had no reason to be ashamed, as he could be of the meanest productions of Hibernian Grub-street.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="6" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-6">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-6-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-6-line-group-1-line-1">As to those <hi rend="italics">fatal verses</hi>, called <hi rend="italics">The lady's dressing-room</hi>, which have so highly inflamed the whole sex, (except a very few of better judgment); as I can by no means justify the vulgar opinion, that seemeth to fix it upon a person so well known for works of a very different nature; so I cannot but lament the prevailing ill taste among us, which is not able to discover that useful satire running through every line, and the matter as decently wrapped up as it is possible the subject could bear.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="7" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-7">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-7-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-7-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Cleanliness</hi> hath, in all polite ages and nations, been esteemed the chief corporal perfection in <hi rend="italics">women</hi>; as it is well known to those who are conversant with the ancient <hi rend="italics">poets</hi>. And so it is still among the young people of judgment and sobriety, when they are disposed to marry. And I do not doubt, but that there is a great number of young ladies in this town and kingdom, who, in reading that poem, find great complacency in their own minds, from a consciousness, that the satirical part in the <hi rend="italics">Lady's dressing-room</hi> doth not in the least affect them.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="8" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-8">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-8-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-8-line-group-1-line-1">Wherefore it is manifest, that no <hi rend="italics">poem</hi> was ever written with a better design for the service of the <hi rend="italics">sex</hi>: wherein our <hi rend="italics">author</hi> hath observed, to a tittle, the precepts of his master Horace; or, indeed, rather hath gone very far beyond him, in the article of <hi rend="italics">decency</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="9" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-9">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-9-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-9-line-group-1-line-1">That great <hi rend="italics">poet</hi>, instructing us what actions are fittest to be produced openly upon the <hi rend="italics">scene</hi>, and which are most proper to be only related to the audience, goeth many lengths beyond the <hi rend="italics">author</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">Lady's dressing-room</hi>; for, at the same instant when he saith, some actions should not appear as done upon the stage, he allows, they may be <hi rend="italics">recited</hi> with pleasure and <hi rend="italics">elegance</hi>; and yet when he cometh to particulars, his recital is extremely gross, and so are his very <hi rend="italics">precepts</hi> which forbid the actions: that if our infinitely more modest <hi rend="italics">author</hi> had imitated his <hi rend="italics">master's style</hi>, the whole world might, with great appearance of reason, have been up in arms against him.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="10" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-10">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-10-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-10-line-group-1-line-1">Therefore to set these two <hi rend="italics">poets</hi> in a true light, I have ventured, for the satisfaction of both sexes, to translate, as literally as I could, ten lines in Horace, upon the very same subject, which our <hi rend="italics">author</hi> hath handled with a decency so far superior to his Roman master.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="11" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-11">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-11-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-11-line-group-1-line-1">To justify the truth of my translation, I desire all fine gentlemen and ladies will appeal from me to the information of the learned, that I may be wholly clear from the least censure of misrepresenting so great an authority; for, indeed, if I have been guilty of any fault, it is in palliating the gross expressions in the original, and softening them very much to the <hi rend="italics">politeness</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">present age</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="12" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-12">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-12-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01008G1-headnote-12-line-group-1-line-1">The Latin is word for word as follows:<hi rend="italics">Aut agitur res in scenis, aut acta refertur.Segnius irritant animos demissa per aurem,Quam quæ sunt oculis subjecta fidelibus, et quæIpse sibi tradit spectator. Non tamen intusDigna geri promes in scenam; multaque tollesEx oculis, quæ mox narret facundia præsens.Nec pueros coram populo Medea trucidet;Aut humana palam coquat exta nefarius Atreus.Aut in avem Progne vertetur, Cadmus in anguem.Quodcunque ostendis mihi sic, incredulus odi</hi>.<note rend="align(center)">The literal translation whereof is thus.<note rend="flush left"></note></note></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-1" n="1">Some ladies <hi rend="italics">do their need</hi> before your face:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-2" n="2">Some only tell the <hi rend="italics">action</hi> and the <hi rend="italics">place</hi>.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-3" n="3">Our mind is less provok'd by what it hears,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-4" n="4">Than what the fact before our eyes appears.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-5" n="5">In closet dark, your <hi rend="italics">cedar-box</hi> be hid;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-6" n="6">Not in a parlour shewn without the lid.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-7" n="7">Some <hi rend="italics">actions</hi> must be always out of sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-8" n="8">Yet, <hi rend="italics">elegantly told</hi>, may give delight.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-9" n="9">Nurse must not hold the child and cry <hi rend="italics">Eee Hee</hi>,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-10" n="10">When Madam and her friends are o'er their tea.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-11" n="11">Atreus, when ladies by, mistakes his wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-12" n="12">In new-born t────s to run a red-hot spit.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-13" n="13">Miss Progne must not cry, <hi rend="italics">A bird, a bird</hi>!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-14" n="14">Before good company, and shew a t────d.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-15" n="15">Cadmus, who voids out worms of monstrous size,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-16" n="16">In meer good manners should deceive our eyes;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-17" n="17">Must do his dirty work behind the scene,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-18" n="18">And ere he shews the <hi rend="italics">vermin</hi>, wipe them clean.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-19" n="19">To bring such odious objects full in view,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-20" n="20">Though <hi rend="italics">fools</hi> may laugh, 'twill make a <hi rend="italics">wise man</hi> spue.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01008G1-line-21" n="21">\CONCLUSION\</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
