<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><hi rend="italics">To their Excellencies &amp;c</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="SB 11AU96"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="069-15L2">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">The humble Petition of </hi>Frances Harris<hi rend="italics">, <lb/> who must starve and die a Maid, if it miscarries</hi>,</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-15L2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-1" n="1"><hi rend="italics">Humbly showeth</hi>,<lb/>That I went to warm my self in <hi rend="italics">Lady Betty</hi>'s chamber, because I was cold;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-2" n="2">and I had, in a purse, seven pounds, four shillings, besides farthings, in money, and gold.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-3" n="3">so, because I had been buying things for my Lady, last night;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-4" n="4">I was resolv'd to tell my mony, to see if it was right:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-5" n="5">now, you must know, because my trunk has a very bad lock,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-6" n="6">therefore all the money I have, which, God knows, is a very small stock,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-7" n="7">I keep in a pocket, ty'd about my middle, next my smock:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-8" n="8">so, when I put up my purse, as God would have it, my smock was unript;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-9" n="9">and, instead of putting it into my pocket, down it slipt.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-10" n="10">then the bell rung, and I went down stairs to put my Lady to bed;</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-11" n="11">when, God knows, I thought my mony as safe as my maiden-head.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-12" n="12">so, when I came up again, I found my pocket very light;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-13" n="13">but, when I searcht, and misst my purse, Lord! I thought I should have sunk outright.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-14" n="14">Lord! <hi rend="italics">Madam</hi>, says <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi>, how d'ye do? Indeed, says I, never worse:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-15" n="15">but pray, <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi>, can you tell what I ha' done with my purse?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-16" n="16">Lord help me, said <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi>, I never stirr'd out of this place!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-17" n="17">Nay, said I, I had it in Lady <hi rend="italics">Betty</hi>'s chamber, that's a plain case.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-18" n="18">so, <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> got me to bed, and cover'd me up warm:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-19" n="19">however, she stole away my garters, that I might do my self no harm.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-20" n="20">so, I tumbled, and tost, all night, as you may very well think;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-21" n="21">but hardly ever set my eyes together, or slept a wink.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-22" n="22">so I was dream'd, methought, that we went, and searcht the folks round;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-23" n="23">and, in a corner of <hi rend="italics">Mrs Duke</hi>'s box, ty'd in a rag, the mony was found.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-24" n="24">so, next morning, we told <hi rend="italics">Whittle</hi>, and he fell a swearing.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-25" n="25">then <hi rend="italics">Mrs Wadgar</hi> and she, you know, is thick o'hearing:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-26" n="26">Dame, said I, as loud as I could bawl, do you know what a loss I have had?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-27" n="27">Nay, said she, my Lord <note place="foot">·<hi rend="italics">Galloway</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italics">Collways</hi> folks are all very sad.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-28" n="28">for my Lord <note place="foot">·<hi rend="italics">Drogheda</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italics">Dromedary</hi> comes o' Tuesday without fail.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-29" n="29">Fugh! said I, but that's not the business I ail.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-30" n="30">says <hi rend="italics">Cary</hi>, says he, I have been a servant this five-and-twenty years, come spring;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-31" n="31">and, in all the places I liv'd, I never heard of such a thing.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-32" n="32">Yes, says the <hi rend="italics">Steward</hi>, when I was at my Lady <hi rend="italics">Shrewsbury's</hi>,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-33" n="33">such a thing as this happen'd, about the time of goosberries.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-34" n="34">So I went to the party suspected, and found her full of grief:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-35" n="35">now you know, of all things in the world, I hate a Thief</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-36" n="36">however, I was resolv'd to bring the discourse slily about;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-37" n="37"><hi rend="italics">Mrs Dukes</hi>, said I, here's an ugly accident has happen'd out:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-38" n="38">'tis not that I value the mony three skips of a louse;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-39" n="39">but the thing I stand upon, is the credit of the house.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-40" n="40">'tis true, seven pound, four shillings, and six-pence, makes a great hole in my wages;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-41" n="41">besides, as they say, Service is no inheritance in these ages.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-42" n="42">now, <hi rend="italics">Mrs Dukes</hi>, you know, and every body understands,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-43" n="43">that, tho' 'tis hard to judge--- Money can't go without hands.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-44" n="44"><hi rend="italics">the Devil take me</hi>, said she, <hi rend="italics">blessing herself</hi>, if ever I saw't!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-45" n="45">so, she roar'd like a Bedlam, as tho' I had call'd her all to naught.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-46" n="46">so, you know, what could I say to her any more;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-47" n="47">I e'en left her, and came away as wise as I was before.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-48" n="48">Well, but then they would have had me gone to the Cunning-man:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-49" n="49">No, said I, 'tis the same thing, the <hi rend="italics">Chaplain</hi> will be here anan.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-50" n="50">so the <hi rend="italics">Chaplain</hi> came in: now the servants say he is my Sweetheart,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-51" n="51">because he's always in my chamber, and I always take his part.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-52" n="52">so, as the Devil would have it, before I was aware, out I blunder'd:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-53" n="53"><hi rend="italics">Parson</hi>, said I, can you cast a nativity, when a body's plunder'd?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-54" n="54">now, you must know, he hates to be call'd <hi rend="italics">Parson</hi>, like the <hi rend="italics">Devil</hi>:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-55" n="55">truly, said he, <hi rend="italics">Mrs Nab</hi>, it might become you to be more civil:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-56" n="56">if your mony be gone, as a learned Divine says, d'ye see,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-57" n="57">you are no Text for my handling, take that from me.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-58" n="58">I was never taken for a Conjurer before, I'd have you to know.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-59" n="59">Lord! said I, don't be angry, I'm sure I never thought you so:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-60" n="60">you know I honour the cloth, I design to be a Parson's wife:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-61" n="61">I never took one in your coat for a conjurer in all my life.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-62" n="62">with that, he twisted his girdle like a rope, as who shou'd say</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-63" n="63">Now you may go hang your self for me, and so went away.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-64" n="64">well, I thought I should have swoon'd: Lord! said I, what shall I do?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-65" n="65">I have lost my mony, and shall lose my True-love too.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-66" n="66">then <hi rend="italics">my Lord</hi> call'd me: <hi rend="italics">Harris</hi>, said <hi rend="italics">my Lord</hi>, don't cry;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-67" n="67">I'll give something towards thy loss; and says <hi rend="italics">my Lady</hi>, so will I.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-68" n="68">oh but, said I, what if, after all, <hi rend="italics">my Chaplain</hi> won't come to:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-69" n="69">for that, he said, (an't please <hi rend="italics">your Excellencies</hi>) I must petition You.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-70" n="70">the premises tenderly consider'd, I desire <hi rend="italics">your Excellencies</hi> protection;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-71" n="71">and that I may have share in next <hi rend="italics">Sunday</hi>'s Collection:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-72" n="72">and, over and above, that I may have <hi rend="italics">your Excellencies</hi> letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-73" n="73">with an order for the <hi rend="italics">Chaplain</hi> aforesaid; or, instead of him, a better:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-74" n="74">and then, <hi rend="italics">your poor Petitioner</hi>, both night and day,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-069-15L2-line-75" n="75">or the <hi rend="italics">Chaplain</hi>, for 'tis his trade, as in duty bound, shall pray.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
