[{"id":"124-13L3","tei":"<?xml version=\"1.0\" encoding=\"utf-8\"?>\n<TEI xmlns=\"http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0\" xml:lang=\"en\">\n  <teiHeader>\n    <fileDesc>\n      <titleStmt>\n        <title><hi rend=\"italics\">Will</hi>'s<hi rend=\"italics\"> Coffee-house, April</hi> 28.</title>\n        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>\n        <principal>James Woolley</principal>\n        <respStmt>\n          <name key=\"CDarkes-Burkey 20JA16\"/>\n          <resp>transcription</resp>\n        </respStmt>\n        <respStmt>\n          <resp>proof corrected</resp>\n          <resp>proof corrected</resp>\n          <name key=\"TNiese 25JA11\"/>\n        </respStmt>\n      </titleStmt>\n      <publicationStmt>\n        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>\n      </publicationStmt>\n      <sourceDesc>\n        <msDesc>\n          <additional/>\n        </msDesc>\n      </sourceDesc>\n    </fileDesc>\n    <encodingDesc>\n      <p/>\n    </encodingDesc>\n    <profileDesc>\n      <langUsage>\n        <language ident=\"en\">English</language>\n      </langUsage>\n    </profileDesc>\n  </teiHeader>\n  <text>\n    <body>\n      <div type=\"book\">\n        <linkGrp type=\"notes\"/>\n        <div n=\"124-13L3\">\n          <head type=\"note\" n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-1\">\n            <lg n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-1-line-group-1\" type=\"headnote\">\n              <l n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1\"><hi rend=\"display-initial\">T</hi>HIS Evening we were entertained with <hi rend=\"italics\">The Old Batchelor</hi>, a Comedy of deserved Reputation. In the Character which gives Name to the Play, there is excellently represented the Reluctance of a battered Debauchee to come into the Trammels of Order and Decency: He neither languishes nor burns, but frets for Love. The Gentlemen of more regular Behavior, are drawn with much Spirit and Wit, and the <hi rend=\"italics\">Drama</hi> introduced by the Dialogue of the first Scene with uncommon, yet natural Conversation. The Part of <hi rend=\"italics\">Fondle-wife</hi> is a lively Image of the unseasonable Fondness of Age and Impotence. But instead of such agreeable Words as these, the Town has this half Age been tormented with the Insects, called <hi rend=\"italics\">Easie Writers</hi>, whose Abilities Mr. <hi rend=\"italics\">Wycherly</hi> one Day described excellently well in one Word: <hi rend=\"italics\">That</hi>, said he, <hi rend=\"italics\">among these Fellows is called</hi> Easy Writing, <hi rend=\"italics\">which any one may easily write</hi>. Such Jantie Scribblers are so justly laughed at for their Sonnets on <hi rend=\"italics\">Phillis</hi> and <hi rend=\"italics\">Chloris</hi>, and Fantastical Descriptions in 'em, that an ingenious Kinsman of mine, of the Family of the <hi rend=\"italics\">Staffs</hi>, Mr. <hi rend=\"italics\">Humphrey Wagstaff</hi> by Name, has, to avoid their Strain, run into a Way perfectly new, and described Things exactly as they happen: He never forms Fields, or Nymphs, or Groves, where they are not, but makes the Incidents just as they really appear. For an Example of it; I stole out of his Manuscript the following Lines: They are a Description of the Morning, but of the Morning in Town; nay, of the Morning at this End of the Town, where my Kinsman at present lodges.</l>\n            </lg>\n          </head>\n          <head type=\"note\" n=\"2\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-2\">\n            <lg n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-2-line-group-1\" type=\"headnote\">\n              <l n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1\">All that I apprehend is, that dear <hi rend=\"italics\">Numps</hi> will be angry that I have published these lines; not that he has any Reason to be ashamed of 'em, but for Fear of those Rogues, the Bane to all excellent Performances, the <hi rend=\"italics\">Imitators</hi>. Therefore, before-hand, I bar all Descriptions of the Evening; as, a Medley of Verses signifying, Grey-Peas are now cried warm: That Wenches now begin to amble round the Passages of the Play-house: Or of Noon; as, That fine Ladies and great Beaus are just yawing out of their Beds and Windows in <hi rend=\"italics\">Pall-Mall</hi>, and so forth. I forewarn also all Persons from encouraging any Draughts after my Cousin; and foretel any Man who shall go about to imitate him, that he will be very insipid. The Family Stock is embarked in this Design, and we will not admit of Counterfeits: Dr. <hi rend=\"italics\">Anderson</hi> and his Heirs enjoy his Pills, Sir <hi rend=\"italics\">William Read</hi> has the Cure of Eyes, and Monsieur <hi rend=\"italics\">Roselli</hi> can only cure the Gout. We pretend to none of these Things; but to examine who and who are together, to tell any mistaken Man he is not what he believes he is, to distinguish Merit, and expose false Pretences to it, is a Liberty our Family has by Law in 'em, from an Inter-marriage with a Daughter of Mr. <hi rend=\"italics\">Scoggin</hi> the famous Droll of the last Century. This Right I design to make use of; but will not encroach upon the above-mentioned Adepts, or any other. At the same Time I shall take all the Privileges I may, as an <hi rend=\"italics\">Englishman</hi>, and will lay hold of the late Act of Naturalization to introduce what I shall think fit from <hi rend=\"italics\">France</hi>. The Use of that Law may, I hope, be extended to People the polite World with new Characters, as well as the Kingdom it self with new Subjects. Therefore an Author of that Nation, called <hi rend=\"italics\">Le Bruyere</hi>, I shall make bold with on such Occasions. The last Person I read of in that Writer, was, Lord <hi rend=\"italics\">Timon. Timon</hi>, says my Author, is the most generous of all Men; but is so hurried away with that strong Impulse of Bestowing, that he confers Benefits without Distinction, and is Munificent without laying Obligations. For all the Unworthy, who receive from him, have so little Sense of this noble Infirmity, that they look upon themselves rather as Partners in a Spoil, than Partakers of a Bounty. The other Day, coming into <hi rend=\"italics\">Paris</hi>, I met <hi rend=\"italics\">Timon</hi> going out on Horseback, attended only be one Servant. It struck me with a sudden Damp, to see a Man of so excellent a Disposition, and that understood making a Figure so very well, so much shortened in his Retinue. But passing by his House, I saw his great Coach break to Pieces before his Door, and, by a strange Inchantment, immediately turned into many different Vehicles. The first was a very pretty Chariot, into which step'd his Lordship's Secretary. The second was hung a little heavier; into that strutted the fat Steward. In an Instant followed a Chaise, which was entered by the Butler. The rest of the Body and Wheels were forthwith changed into Go-carts, and ran away with by the Nurses and Brats of the rest of the Family. What makes these Misfortunes in the Affairs of <hi rend=\"italics\">Timon</hi> the more astonishing, is, That he has a better Understanding than those who cheat him; so that a Man knows not which more to wonder at, the Indifference of the Master, or the Impudence of the Servant.</l>\n            </lg>\n          </head>\n          <head type=\"note\" n=\"3\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-3\">\n            <lg n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-3-line-group-1\" type=\"headnote\">\n              <l n=\"1\" xml:id=\"spp-124-13L3-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1\"></l>\n            </lg>\n          </head>\n          <lg n=\"1\"><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-1\" n=\"1\"><hi rend=\"italics\">Now hardly here and there an Hackney-Coach</hi></l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-2\" n=\"2\">Appearing, show'd the Ruddy Morn's Approach.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-3\" n=\"3\">Now Betty from her Master's Bed had flown</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-4\" n=\"4\">And softly stole to discompose her own.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-5\" n=\"5\">The Slipshod 'Prentice from his Master's Door,</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-6\" n=\"6\">Had par'd the Street, and sprinkled round the Floor.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-7\" n=\"7\">Had par'd the Street, and sprinkled round the Floor.Now </l>Moll<hi rend=\"italics\"> had whirl'd her Mop with dext'rous Airs,</hi><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-8\" n=\"8\">Prepar'd to scrub the Entry and the Stairs.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-9\" n=\"9\">The Youth with broomy Stumps began to trace</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-10\" n=\"10\">The Kennel Edge, where Wheels had worn the Place.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-11\" n=\"11\">The Smallcoal-Man was heard with Cadence deep,</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-12\" n=\"12\">Till drown'd in shriller Notes of Chimney-sweep.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-13\" n=\"13\">Duns at his Lorship's Gate began to meet;</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-14\" n=\"14\">Duns at his Lorship's Gate began to meet;And Brickdust </l>Moll<hi rend=\"italics\"> had scream'd through half a Street.</hi><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-15\" n=\"15\">The Turnkey now his Flock returning sees,</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-16\" n=\"16\">Duly let out a'Nights to steal for Fees.</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-17\" n=\"17\">The watchful Bailiffs take their silent Stands;</l><l xml:id=\"swift-124-13L3-line-18\" n=\"18\">The watchful Bailiffs take their silent Stands;And School-boys lag with Satchels in their Hands</l>.</lg>\n        </div>\n      </div>\n    </body>\n  </text>\n</TEI>\n"}]