<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>From <hi rend="italics">Thursday April</hi> 28. to <hi rend="italics">Saturday April 30</hi>. N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 9.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="AGendler 13MR05"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>tochk items √'d JW 5JA06 in situ; ed. JW 27OC16</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="124-10L6">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">But instead of such agreeable Works as these, the Town has this half Age been tormented with Insects call'd <hi rend="italics">Easie Writers</hi>, whose Abilities Mr. <hi rend="italics">Wycherly</hi> one Day describ'd excellently well in one Word: <hi rend="italics">That, </hi>said he<hi rend="italics">, among these Fellows is call'd </hi>Easy Writing<hi rend="italics">, which any one may easily write</hi>. Such Janty Scriblers are so justly laugh'd at for their Sonnets on <hi rend="italics">Phillis</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Chloris</hi>, and Fantastical Descriptions in 'em, that an ingenious Kinsman of mine, of the Family of the <hi rend="italics">Staffs</hi>, Mr. <hi rend="italics">Humphrey Wagstaff</hi> by Name, has, to avoid their Strain, run into a Way perfectly new, and describ'd Things exactly as they happen: He never forms Fields, or Nymphs, or Groves, where they are not, but makes the Incidents just as they really appear. For an Example of it; I stole out of his Manuscript the following Lines: They are a Description of the Morning, but of the Morning in Town; nay, of the Morning at this end of the Town, where my Kinsman at present lodges.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">	All that I apprehend is, that Dear <hi rend="italics">Numps</hi> will be angry I have publish'd these Lines; not that he has any Reason to be asham'd of 'em, but for fear of those Rogues, the Bane to all excellent Performances, the <hi rend="italics">Imitators</hi>. Therefore, before-hand, I barr all Descriptions of the Evening; as, a Medley of Verses signifying Grey Peas are now cri'd warm; That Wenches now begin to amble round the Passages of the Play-house: Or of Noon; as, That fine Ladies and great Beaux are just yawning out of their Beds and Windows in <hi rend="italics">Pall-Mall</hi>, and so forth. I forewarn also all Persons from encouraging any Draughts after my Cousin; and foretel any Man who shall go about to imitate him, that he will be very insipid.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-124-10L6-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-1" n="1">Now hardly here and there an Hackney-Coach</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-2" n="2">Appearing, show'd the Ruddy Morn's Approach.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-3" n="3">Now <hi rend="italics">Betty</hi> from her Master's Bed had flown,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-4" n="4">And softly stole to discompose her own.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-5" n="5">The Slipshod Prentice from his Master's Door,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-6" n="6">Had par'd the Street, and sprinkled round the Floor.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-7" n="7">Now <hi rend="italics">Moll</hi> had whirl'd her Mop with dext'rous Airs,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-8" n="8">Prepar'd to scrub the Entry and the Stairs.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-9" n="9">The Youth with broomy Stumps began to trace</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-10" n="10">The Kennel Edge, where Wheels had worn the Place.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-11" n="11">The Smallcoal-Man was heard with Cadence deep,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-12" n="12">Till drown'd in shriller Notes of Chimney-sweep.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-13" n="13">Duns at his Lordship's Gate began to meet:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-14" n="14">And Brickdust <hi rend="italics">Moll</hi> had scream'd through half a Street.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-15" n="15">The Turn-key now his Flock returning sees,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-16" n="16">Duly let out a' Nights to steal for Fees.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-17" n="17">The watchful Bailiffs take their silent Stands;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-124-10L6-line-18" n="18">And School-boys lag with Satchels in their Hands.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
