<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>APOLLO TO THE DEAN. 1720.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="AGendler 30JL04"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="263-14W2">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">T<hi rend="small-caps">HIS</hi> was written by Swift, in reply to the verses on the windows.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-263-14W2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-1" n="1">R<hi rend="small-caps">IGHT</hi> trusty, and so forth── we let you to know</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-2" n="2">We are very ill used by you mortals below.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-3" n="3">For, first, I have often by chemists been told,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-4" n="4">Though I know nothing on't, it is I that make gold;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-5" n="5">Which when you have got, you so carefully hide it,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-6" n="6">That, since I was born, I hardly have spied it.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-7" n="7">Then it must be allow'd, that, whenever I shine,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-8" n="8">I forward the grass, and I ripen the vine;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-9" n="9">To me the good fellows apply for relief,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-10" n="10">Without whom they could get neither claret nor beef:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-11" n="11">Yet their wine and their victuals, those curmudgeon lubbards</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-12" n="12">Lock up from my sight in cellars and cupboards.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-13" n="13">That I have an ill eye, they wickedly think,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-14" n="14">And taint all their meat, and sour all their drink.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-15" n="15">But, thirdly and lastly, it must be allow'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-16" n="16">I alone can inspire the poetical crowd:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-17" n="17">This is gratefully own'd by each boy in the College,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-18" n="18">Whom, if I inspire, it is not to my knowledge.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-19" n="19">This every pretender to rhyme will admit,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-20" n="20">Without troubling his head about judgment or wit.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-21" n="21">These gentlemen use me with kindness and freedom,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-22" n="22">And as for their works, when I please I may read 'em.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-23" n="23">They lie open on purpose on counters and stalls,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-24" n="24">And the titles I view, when I shine on the walls.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-25" n="25">But a comrade of yours, that traitor Delany,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-26" n="26">Whom I for your sake love better than any,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-27" n="27">And, of my mere motion, and special good grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-28" n="28">Intended in time to succeed in your place,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-29" n="29">On Tuesday the tenth, seditiously came,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-30" n="30">With a certain false trait'ress, one Stella by name,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-31" n="31">To the Deanery-house, and on the north glass,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-32" n="32">Where for fear of the cold I never can pass,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-33" n="33">Then and there, <hi rend="italics">vi et armis</hi>, with a certain utensil,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-34" n="34">Of value five shillings, in English a pencil,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-35" n="35">Did maliciously, falsely, and traitorously write,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-36" n="36">While Stella, aforesaid, stood by with a light.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-37" n="37">My sister has lately deposed upon oath,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-38" n="38">That she stopt in her course to look at them both;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-39" n="39">That Stella was helping, abetting, and aiding;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-40" n="40">And still as he writ, stood smiling and reading:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-41" n="41">That her eyes were as bright as myself at noon-day,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-42" n="42">But her graceful black locks were all mingled with grey:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-43" n="43">And by the description, I certainly know,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-44" n="44">'Tis the nymph that I courted some ten years ago;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-45" n="45">Whom when I with the best of my talents endued,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-46" n="46">On her promise of yielding, she acted the prude:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-47" n="47">That some verses were writ with felonious intent,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-48" n="48">Direct to the north, where I never yet went:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-49" n="49">That the letters appear'd reversed through the pane,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-50" n="50">But in Stella's bright eyes they were placed right again;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-51" n="51">Wherein she distinctly could read every line,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-52" n="52">And presently guess'd that the fancy was mine.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-53" n="53">She can swear to the person, whom oft she has seen</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-54" n="54">At night between Cavan Street and College Green.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-55" n="55">Now you see why his verses so seldom are shewn,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-56" n="56">The reason is plain, they are none of his own;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-57" n="57">And observe while you live that no man is shy</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-58" n="58">To discover the goods he came honestly by.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-59" n="59">If I light on a thought, he will certainly steal it,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-60" n="60">And when he has got it, find ways to conceal it.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-61" n="61">Of all the fine things he keeps in the dark,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-62" n="62">There's scarce one in ten but what has my mark;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-63" n="63">And let them be seen by the world if he dare,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-64" n="64">I'll make it appear they are all stolen ware.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-65" n="65">But as for the poem he writ on your sash,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-66" n="66">I think I have now got him under my lash;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-67" n="67">My sister transcribed it last night to his sorrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-68" n="68">And the public shall see't, if I live till to-morrow.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-69" n="69">Through the zodiac around, it shall quickly be spread</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-70" n="70">In all parts of the globe where your language is read.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-71" n="71">He knows very well, I ne'er gave a refusal,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-72" n="72">When he ask'd for my aid in the forms that are usual;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-73" n="73">But the secret is this; I did lately intend</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-74" n="74">To write a few verses on you as my friend:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-75" n="75">I studied a fortnight, before I could find,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-76" n="76">As I rode in my chariot, a thought to my mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-77" n="77">And resolved the next winter (for that is my time,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-78" n="78">When the days are at shortest) to get it in rhyme;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-79" n="79">Till then it was lock'd in my box at Parnassus;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-80" n="80">When that subtle companion, in hopes to surpass us,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-81" n="81">Conveys out my paper of hints by a trick,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-82" n="82">(For I think in my conscience he deals with old Nick,)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-83" n="83">And from my own stock provided with topics,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-84" n="84">He gets to a window beyond both the tropics,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-85" n="85">There out of my sight, just against the north zone,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-86" n="86">Writes down my conceits, and then calls them his own;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-87" n="87">And you, like a booby, the bubble can swallow:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-88" n="88">Now who but Delany can write like Apollo?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-89" n="89">High treason by statute! yet here you object,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-90" n="90">He only stole hints, but the verse is correct;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-91" n="91">Though the thought be Apollo's, 'tis finely express'd;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-92" n="92">So a thief steals my horse, and has him well dress'd.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-93" n="93">Now whereas the said criminal seems past repentance,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-94" n="94">We Phœbus think fit to proceed to the sentence.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-95" n="95">Since Delany has dared, like Prometheus his sire,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-96" n="96">To climb to our region, and thence to steal fire;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-97" n="97">We order a vulture in shape of the spleen,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-98" n="98">To prey on his liver, but not to be seen.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-99" n="99">And we order our subjects of every degree</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-100" n="100">To believe all his verses were written by me:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-101" n="101">And under the pain of our highest displeasure,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-102" n="102">To call nothing his but the rhyme and the measure.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-103" n="103">And, lastly, for Stella, just out of her prime,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-104" n="104">I'm too much avenged already by time.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-105" n="105">In return to her scorn, I sent her diseases,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-106" n="106">But will now be her friend whenever she pleases.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-107" n="107">And the gifts I bestow'd her will find her a lover,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-263-14W2-line-108" n="108">Though she lives till she's grey as a badger all over.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
