<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="italics">A Serious Poem upon William Wood</hi>
        </title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="334-ROGP">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">BRAZIER, TINKER, HARDWARE-MAN, COINER, COUNTERFEITER, FOUNDER AND ESQUIRE&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-334-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-1" n="1">When foes are o'ercome, we preserve them from slaughter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-2" n="2">To be hewers of wood and drawers of water,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-3" n="3">Now, although to draw water is not very good,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-4" n="4">Yet we all should rejoice to be hewers of wood.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-5" n="5">I own it hath often provoked me to mutter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-6" n="6">That, a rogue so obscure should make such a clutter,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-7" n="7">But ancient philosophers wisely remark,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-8" n="8">That old rotten wood will shine in the dark.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-9" n="9">The heathens, we read, had gods made of wood,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-10" n="10">Who could do them no harm, if they did them no good:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-11" n="11">But this idol Wood may do us great evil,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-12" n="12">Their gods were of wood, but our Wood is the devil:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-13" n="13">To cut down fine wood is a very bad thing,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-14" n="14">And yet we all know much gold it will bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-15" n="15">Then if cutting down Wood brings money good store,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-16" n="16">Our money to keep, let us cut down one more.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-17" n="17"><lb/>Now hear an old tale. There anciently stood</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-18" n="18">(I forget in what church) an image of wood;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-19" n="19">Concerning this image there went a prediction,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-20" n="20">It would burn a whole forest; nor was it a fiction;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-21" n="21">'Twas cut into faggots, and put to the flame,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-22" n="22">To burn an old friar, one Forest by name.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-23" n="23">My tale is a wise one if well understood,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-24" n="24">Find you but the friar, and I'll find the Wood.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-25" n="25"><lb/>I hear among scholars there is a great doubt</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-26" n="26">From what kind of tree this Wood was hewn out.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-27" n="27">Teague made a good pun by a brogue in his speech,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-28" n="28">And said: 'By my shoul he's the son of a beech':</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-29" n="29">Some call him a thorn, the curse of a nation,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-30" n="30">As thorns were designed to be from the creation.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-31" n="31">Some think him cut out from the poisonous yew,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-32" n="32">Beneath whose ill shade no plant ever grew.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-33" n="33">Some say he's a birch, a thought very odd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-34" n="34">For none but a dunce would come under his rod.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-35" n="35">But I'll tell you the secret, and pray do not blab,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-36" n="36">He is an old stump cut out of a crab,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-37" n="37">And England has put this crab to hard use,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-38" n="38">To cudgel our bones, and for drink give us verjuice;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-39" n="39">And therefore his witnesses justly may boast</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-40" n="40">That none are more properly knights of the post.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-41" n="41"><lb/>But here Mr Wood complains that we mock,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-42" n="42">Though he may be a blockhead, he is no real block.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-43" n="43">He can eat, drink and sleep; now and then for a friend</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-44" n="44">He'll not be too proud an old kettle to mend;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-45" n="45">He can lie like a courtier, and think it no scorn,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-46" n="46">When gold's to be got, to forswear and suborn.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-47" n="47">He can rap his own raps, and has the true sapience</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-48" n="48">To turn a good penny to twenty bad ha'pence.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-49" n="49">Then in spite of your sophistry, honest Will Wood</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-50" n="50">Is a man of this world all true flesh and blood;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-51" n="51">So you are but in jest, and you will not I hope</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-52" n="52">Unman the poor knave for the sake of a trope.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-53" n="53">'Tis a metaphor known to every plain thinker,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-54" n="54">Just as when we say, the devil's a tinker,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-55" n="55">Which cannot in literal sense be made good,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-56" n="56">Unless by the devil we mean Mr Wood.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-57" n="57"><lb/>But some will object, that the devil oft spoke</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-58" n="58">In heathenish times from the trunk of an oak:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-59" n="59">And, since we must grant, there never were known</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-60" n="60">More heathenish times than those of our own;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-61" n="61">Perhaps you will say, 'tis the devil that puts</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-62" n="62">The words in Wood's mouth, or speaks from his guts:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-63" n="63">And then your old argument still will return:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-64" n="64">Howe'er let us try him and see how he'll burn.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-65" n="65">You'll pardon me sir, your cunning I smoke,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-66" n="66">But Wood I assure you is no heart of oak;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-67" n="67">And instead of the devil, this son of perdition</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-68" n="68">Hath joined with himself two hags in commission.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-69" n="69"><lb/>I ne'er could endure my talent to smother,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-70" n="70">I told you one tale, I will tell you another.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-71" n="71">A joiner to fasten a saint in a niche,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-72" n="72">Bored a large auger-hole in the image's breech;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-73" n="73">But finding the statue to make no complaint,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-74" n="74">He would ne'er be convinced it was a true saint:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-75" n="75">When the true Wood arrives, as he soon will no doubt,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-76" n="76">(For that's but a sham Wood they carry about)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-77" n="77">What stuff he is made on you quickly may find,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-78" n="78">If you make the same trial, and bore him behind;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-79" n="79">I'll hold you a groat, when you wimble his bum,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-80" n="80">He'll bellow as loud as a devil in a drum:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-81" n="81">From me I declare you shall have no denial,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-82" n="82">And there can be no harm in making a trial;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-83" n="83">And when to the joy of your hearts he has roared,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-84" n="84">You may show him about for a new groaning board.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-85" n="85"><lb/>Now ask me a question. How came it to pass</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-86" n="86">Wood got so much copper? He got it by brass;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-87" n="87">This Brass was a dragon (observe what I tell ye)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-88" n="88">This dragon had gotten two sows in its belly;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-89" n="89">I know you will say, this is all heathen Greek;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-90" n="90">I own it, and therefore I leave you to seek.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-91" n="91"><lb/>I often have seen two plays very good,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-92" n="92">Called, <hi rend="italics">Love in a Tub</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Love in a Wood</hi>.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-93" n="93">These comedies twain friend Wood will contrive</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-94" n="94">On the scene of this land very soon to revive.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-95" n="95">First, <hi rend="italics">Love in a Tub</hi>: 'squire Wood has in store</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-96" n="96">Strong tubs for his raps, two thousand and more;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-97" n="97">These raps he will honestly dig out with shovels,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-98" n="98">And sell them for gold, or he can't show his love else.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-99" n="99">Wood swears he will do it for Ireland's good,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-100" n="100">Then can you deny it is <hi rend="italics">Love in a Wood</hi>?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-101" n="101">However, if critics find fault with the phrase,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-102" n="102">I hope you will own it is <hi rend="italics">Love in a Maze</hi>;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-103" n="103">For when to express a friend's love we are willing,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-104" n="104">We never say more than, your love is a million;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-105" n="105">But with honest Wood's love there is no contending,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-106" n="106">'Tis fifty round millions of love, and a mending.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-107" n="107">Then in his first love why should he be crossed?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-108" n="108">I hope he will find that no love is lost.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-109" n="109"><lb/>Hear one story more, and then I will stop.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-110" n="110">I dreamt Wood was told he should die by a drop:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-111" n="111">So methought, he resolved no liquor to taste,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-112" n="112">For fear the first drop might as well be his last:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-113" n="113">But dreams are like oracles, hard to explain 'em,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-114" n="114">For it proved that he died of a drop at Kilmainham:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-115" n="115">I waked with delight, and not without hope,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-116" n="116">Very soon to see Wood drop down from a rope.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-117" n="117">How he and how we at each other should grin!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-118" n="118">'Tis kindness to hold a friend up by the chin;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-119" n="119">But soft, says the herald, I cannot agree;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-120" n="120">For metal on metal is false heraldry:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-121" n="121">Why that may be true, yet Wood upon wood,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-334-ROGP-line-122" n="122">I'll maintain with my life, is heraldry good.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
