<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="spp-578-17H3-title-1">THE<lb/>  DAY OF JUDGEMENT<ref target="#spp-578-17H3-footnote-title-1">1</ref><note n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-footnote-title-1" place="foot">This Poem now appears for the first time in any collection of the Dean's works. that is the genuine prodcution of his masterly pen, lord <hi rend="italics">Chesterfield</hi> thus bears testimony: “I cannot but acknowledge the obligation we have to you, sir, for the light which you have thrown upon the follies and outrages of the different sects. The weapons you employ against those madmen, or rather those impostors, are the only fuitable ones; to make use of any others, would be imitating them: they must be attacked by ridicule, and punished with contempt. <hi rend="italics">A propos</hi> of those fanaticks; I send you here inclosed, a piece upon that subject, written by the late Dean <hi rend="italics">Swift</hi>: I believe you will not dislike it. You will easily guess why it never was printed: it is authentic; and I have the original in his own hand-writing. His <hi rend="italics">Jupiter</hi>, at the day of judgement, treats them as you do, and as they deserve to be treated.” Letter (<hi rend="small-caps">CCLIV</hi>.) to M. <hi rend="italics">Voltaire, Aug</hi>. 27, 1752. ──── Two Letters from M. <hi rend="italics">Voltaire</hi> to Dr. <hi rend="italics">Swift</hi> are printed in vol. XX. of this collection, p. 294; in one of which he tells the Dean, “That he owed the love he bore to the <hi rend="italics">English</hi> language to his writings;” and in both solicits subscriptions to his <hi rend="italics">Henriade</hi>. A third letter is in vol. XXI. p. 278 expressed in the highest terms of esteem. In a recent publication of M. <hi rend="italics">Voltaire</hi>, he has thus described the Dean: “ <hi rend="italics">Swift</hi> was much less learned than <hi rend="italics">Rabelais</hi>; but his wit is more pointed, mor delicate: he is the <hi rend="italics">Rabelais</hi> of high life.” ── Again, “The <hi rend="italics">Tale of a Tub</hi> is wretchedly translated into <hi rend="italics">French</hi>; it was not indeed possible to do justice to the humour with which it is seasoned; which turns often on incidents unknown in <hi rend="italics">France</hi>, and often on a certain play of words peculiar to the <hi rend="italics">English</hi>language; for example the word <hi rend="italics">Bull</hi> signifies in <hi rend="italics">English</hi> both the <hi rend="italics">Pope's Bull</hi> and the animal of that name. Such words are a source of ambiguity and pleasantry, entirely lost upon a <hi rend="italics">French</hi> reader.” Letters to the Prince of ****, 1768, p. 44 ── See Lord <hi rend="italics">Chesterfield</hi>'s opinion of <hi rend="italics">Voltaire</hi>'s writings, and particularly of <hi rend="italics">The Henriade</hi>, which his lordship very highly commends, and says, “He never read any Epic poem with near so much pleasure;” Letters <hi rend="small-caps">CCLIV. CCLIX. N.</hi></note>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="ATotoreanu 14OC13"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-578-17H3-footnote-title-1 #spp-578-17H3-title-1"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="578-17H3">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-578-17H3-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-1" n="1"><hi rend="display-initial">W</hi>ITH a whirl of thought oppress'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-2" n="2">I sunk from reverie to rest.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-3" n="3">An horrid vision seiz'd my head,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-4" n="4">I saw the graves give up their dead!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-5" n="5"><hi rend="italics">Jove</hi>, arm'd with terrors, bursts the skies,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-6" n="6">And thunder roars, and lightning flies!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-7" n="7">Amaz'd, confus'd, its fate unknown,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-8" n="8">The world stands trembling at his throne!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-9" n="9">While each pale sinner hung his head,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-10" n="10"><hi rend="italics">Jove</hi> nodding, shook the heavens, and said:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-11" n="11">“Offending race of human-kind,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-12" n="12">“By nature, reason, learning, blind;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-13" n="13">“You who, thro'frailty, stepp'd aside;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-14" n="14">“And you who never fell, <hi rend="italics">thro' pride</hi>;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-15" n="15">“You who, in different sects, were shamm'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-16" n="16">“And come to see each other damn'd;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-17" n="17">“(So some folk told you, but they knew</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-18" n="18">“No more of <hi rend="italics">Jove</hi>'s designs than you)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-19" n="19">“ ── The world's mad business now is o'er,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-20" n="20">“And I resent these pranks no more.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-21" n="21">“── I to such blockheads set my wit?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-578-17H3-line-22" n="22">“I damn such fools! ── Go, go, you're <hi rend="italics">bit</hi>.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
