<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A MODEST<lb/>  DEFENCE<lb/>  OF A LATE<lb/>  POEM<lb/>  By an unknown Author, call'd,<lb/>  The LADY's <hi rend="italics">Dressing-ROOM</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="TNiese 21DE10"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="P01032D1">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">A</hi> Poem, or Pamphlet published in this Kingdom without a Name, will not long want one, if the Paper makes any Noise.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">There is a certain <hi rend="italics">Person</hi> of Distinction among us, who is conjectured to have written many Things, both in Prose and Verse, for the Service of the Nation, which, undoubtedly, were published with his own Consent. It is also believed, that he hath composed others occasionally, for the Amusement of himself and a few intimate Friends; which by the Indiscretion of others, were, from stolen and incorrect Copies, <hi rend="italics">dragged into Light</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">But, I hold it for certain, that a much greater Number have, by the Boldness of <hi rend="italics">Printers</hi>, and the Want of Judgment in <hi rend="italics">Readers</hi>, been charged upon that <hi rend="italics">Author</hi>, wherein he never had the smallest Finger, as I am assured he hath often declared; and, which is remarkable, was as free in disowning some Writings charged upon him, of which he had no Reason to be ashamed as he could be of the meanest Productions of <hi rend="italics">Hibernian Grub-street</hi>: Of which I shall instance only one Pamphlet, which hath been very well received, as it justly deserved. It is entitled, <hi rend="italics">An Infallible Scheme to pay the Nation's Debts, by a Tax upon Vice</hi>; which he disclaimed any Share in, at the same Time giving it due Praises. And, I find, the <hi rend="italics">true Author</hi> of that Pamphlet lyes yet concealed; which is a Happiness that few <hi rend="italics">Writers</hi> of any Distinction can arrive at, whether by their own Indiscretion, or that of their Friends I shall not determine.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-4">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1">As to those <hi rend="italics">fatal Verses</hi> called the <hi rend="italics">Lady's Dressing-Room</hi>, which have so highly inflamed the whole Sex, (except a very few of better Judgment) as I can by no Means justify the vulgar Opinion, that seems to fix it upon a Person, so well known for Works of a very different Nature; so I cannot but lament the prevailing ill Taste among us which is not able to discover that useful Satyr running through every Line, and the Matter as decently wrapp'd up, as it is possible the Subject could bear.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="5" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-5">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-5-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-5-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Cleanliness</hi> hath, in all polite Ages and Nations, been esteemed the chief corporeal Perfection in <hi rend="italics">Women</hi>, as it is well known to those who are conversant with the antient <hi rend="italics">Poets</hi>. And so it is still among the young People of Judgment and Sobriety, when they are disposed to marry. And I do not doubt, but that there is a great Number of young Ladies in this Town and Kingdom, who in reading that Poem, find great Complacency in their own Minds, from a Consciousness that the Satyrical Part in the <hi rend="italics">Lady's Dressing-Room</hi>, does not in the least affect them.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="6" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-6">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-6-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-6-line-group-1-line-1">Wherefore it is manifest, that no <hi rend="italics">Poem</hi> was ever written with a better Design for the Service of the <hi rend="italics">Sex</hi>: Wherein our <hi rend="italics">Author</hi> hath observed to a Tittle, the Precepts of his Master <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>; or, indeed, rather hath gone very far beyond him, in the Article of <hi rend="italics">Decency</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="7" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-7">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-7-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-7-line-group-1-line-1">That great <hi rend="italics">Poet</hi>, instructing us what Actions are fittest to be produced openly upon the <hi rend="italics">Scene</hi>, and which are most proper to be only related to the Audience, goes many Lengths beyond the <hi rend="italics">Author</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">Lady's Dressing-Room</hi>; for at the same Instant when he says, some Actions should not appear as done upon the Stage, he allows, they may be <hi rend="italics">recited</hi> with <hi rend="italics">Pleasure</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Elegance</hi>; and yet when he comes to Particulars, his Recital is extreamly gross, and so are his very <hi rend="italics">Precepts</hi> which forbid the Actions: That if our infinitely more modest <hi rend="italics">Author</hi> had imitated his <hi rend="italics">Master's Stile</hi>, the whole World might with great Appearance of Reason, have been up in Arms against him.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="8" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-8">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-8-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-8-line-group-1-line-1">Therefore, to set these two <hi rend="italics">Poets</hi> in a true Light, I have ventured, for the Satisfaction of both Sexes, to translate, as literally as I could, ten Lines in <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, upon the very same Subject, which our <hi rend="italics">Author</hi> hath handled with a Decency so far superior to his <hi rend="italics">Roman</hi> Master.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="9" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-9">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-9-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-9-line-group-1-line-1">To justify the Truth of my Translation, I desire all fine Gentlemen and Ladies will appeal from me to the Information of the Learned, that I may be wholly clear from the least Censure of misrepresenting so great an Authority; for, indeed, if I have been guilty of any Fault, it is in palliating the gross Expressions in the Original, and soft'ning them very much to the <hi rend="italics">Politeness</hi> of the <hi rend="italics">present Age</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="10" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-10">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-10-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-10-line-group-1-line-1">The <hi rend="italics">Latin</hi> is Word for Word as follows.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="11" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-11">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-11-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-11-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Aut agitur res in scenis, aut acta refertur. <lb/> Segnius irritant animos demissa per aurem, <lb/> Quam quæ sunt oculis subject a fidelibus, &amp; quæ <lb/> Ipse sibi tradit spectator. Non tamen intus <lb/> Digna geri promes in scenam: Multaq; tolles <lb/> Ex oculis quæ mox narret facundia præsens. <lb/> Nec pueros coram populo </hi>Medea<hi rend="italics"> trucidet; <lb/> Aut humana palam coquat exta nefarius </hi>Atreus<hi rend="italics">. <lb/> Aut in avem </hi>Progne<hi rend="italics"> vertetur, </hi>Cadmus<hi rend="italics"> in anguem. <lb/> Quodcunq; ostendis mihi sic, incredulus odi.</hi></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="12" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-12">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-12-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-12-line-group-1-line-1">The literal Translation whereof is thus.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="13" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-13">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-13-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-13-line-group-1-line-1">I desire the Reader will compare the least exceptionable Lines in the <hi rend="italics">Lady's Dressing-Room</hi> with the least offensive of these in <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>; although purged by me, as much as could consist with preserving the true Sense of the Original: Yet this was the great <hi rend="italics">Master of Politeness</hi> in the <hi rend="italics">Roman</hi> Empire, at the Time it flourished most in <hi rend="italics">Arts</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Arms</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="14" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-14">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-14-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-14-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, you see, makes Use of the plain slovenly Words, which our decent <hi rend="italics">Irish Poet</hi> industriously avoids, and skips over a Hundred dirty Places, without fowling his Shoes. <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, on the contrary, plainly calls a <hi rend="italics">Spade</hi>, a <hi rend="italics">Spade</hi>, when there was not the least Necessity; and when, with equal Ease as well as Significancy, he might have express'd his Meaning in comely Terms, fit for the nicest Ears of a <hi rend="italics">Queen</hi> or a <hi rend="italics">Dutchess</hi>.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="15" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-15">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-15-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-P01032D1-headnote-15-line-group-1-line-1">I do, therefore, positively decide in favour of our <hi rend="italics">Hibernian Bard</hi>, upon the Article of <hi rend="italics">Decency</hi>; and am ready to defend my Proposition against all Mankind; that in the ten Lines of <hi rend="italics">Horace</hi>, here faithfully and favourably translated, there are ten Times more <hi rend="italics">slovenly Expressions</hi>, than in the whole <hi rend="italics">Poem</hi> called the <hi rend="italics">Lady's Dressing Room</hi>; and for the Truth of this Proposition, I am ready to appeal to all the young Ladies of the Kingdom, or to such a <hi rend="italics">Committee</hi> as my very Adversaries shall appoint.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-1" n="1">Some Ladies <hi rend="italics">do their Need</hi> before your Face;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-2" n="2">Some only tell the <hi rend="italics">Action</hi>, and the <hi rend="italics">Place</hi>.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-3" n="3">Our Mind is less provok'd by what it hears,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-4" n="4">Than when the <hi rend="italics">Fact</hi> before our Eyes appears.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-5" n="5">In Closet dark, your <hi rend="italics">Cedar-box</hi> be hid;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-6" n="6">Not in a Parlour shown without the Lid.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-7" n="7">Some <hi rend="italics">Actions</hi> must be always out of Sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-8" n="8">Yet <hi rend="italics">elegantly told</hi>, may give Delight.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-9" n="9">Nurse must not hold the Child, and cry <hi rend="italics">Eee, Hee</hi>,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-10" n="10">When Madam and her Friends are o'er their Tea.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-11" n="11"><hi rend="italics">Atreus</hi>, with Ladies by, mistakes his Wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-12" n="12">In new-born T---s to run a red-hot Spit.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-13" n="13">Miss <hi rend="italics">Progne</hi> must not cry, <hi rend="italics">a Bird, a Bird!</hi></l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-14" n="14">Before good Company, and shew a -----.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-15" n="15"><hi rend="italics">Cadmus</hi>, who voids out Worms of monst'rous Size,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-16" n="16">In mere good Manners should deceive our Eyes;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-17" n="17">Must do his dirty Work behind the Scene,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-18" n="18">And e'er he shews the <hi rend="italics">Vermin</hi>, wipe them clean.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-19" n="19">To bring such odious Objects full in View,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-P01032D1-line-20" n="20">Though <hi rend="italics">Fools</hi> may laugh, will make a <hi rend="italics">wise Man</hi> spew.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
