<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>AN<lb/>  ANSWRE<lb/>  TO THE<lb/>  <hi rend="black-letter">Christmass-Box</hi>.<lb/>  IN DEFENCE OF<lb/>  Docter <hi rend="italics">D──n──y</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="TNiese 23NO10"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="S175A246">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">By R────t B────r.&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">────·────·────·──── <hi rend="italics">Si, Perguma dextrâ <lb/> Defendi possent, etiam hac defensa fuissent</hi> En: 2.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-S175A246-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1"><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-1" n="1"><hi rend="display-initial">Y</hi>E damnable dunces, ye Criblers what mean ye,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-2" n="2">To fall with your dogrell on Doctor D-n-y.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-3" n="3">Such poor silly Criticks as you may go Whistle,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-4" n="4">You ne'er can run-down his familiar Epistle,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-5" n="5">That <hi rend="italics">brilliant</hi> Epistle which glitters and <hi rend="italics">shines</hi>,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-6" n="6">In Musick, in Numbers, in Diction, in Lines,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-7" n="7">In Substance, in Spirit, in Force, and in Witt,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-8" n="8">In Complements such as Augustus might fit,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-9" n="9">Tho' what he has said of his patron is faint</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-10" n="10">Nor wonder, since no Man his virtues can paint,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-11" n="11">For no Poet ever attempts to express;</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-12" n="12">A man truely great, but he must make him less,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-13" n="13">Besides he divided, he gave the one half,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-14" n="14">Of all the Encomiums to himself and Sir Ralph,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-15" n="15">O! Wonderfull Prowess of genius, when he</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-16" n="16">With so little trouble cou'd Complement three!</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-17" n="17">His Lord and the Speaker shall live in his Poem,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-18" n="18">Six thousand Years after all readers shall know 'em,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-19" n="19">While Pindar, and Horace, and Virgil forgotten</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-20" n="20">Shall be like their Heroes, Sunk bury'd &amp; rotten</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-21" n="21">For all other Authors his Writings shall banish,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-22" n="22">Like Ghosts at the sight of the Day-light they'll vanish,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-23" n="23">His glorious Epistle so shining and high</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-24" n="24">Shall be like his Phœbus, that Lord of the Sky,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-25" n="25">Who, when on his <hi rend="italics">Chrysolithe</hi> Throne he appears,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-26" n="26">A Star dare not peep in the Sky for it's Ears.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-27" n="27">Now a word by the by; for I think it my duty</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-28" n="28">Since you're so Mistaken to point out each Beauty,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-29" n="29">Observe with what judgment he shews this our Isle,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-30" n="30">A patron so artfull our Cares can beguile;</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-31" n="31">How that very pievish, Cross grumbler the Dean,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-32" n="32">Does nothing at Court but of Courtiers Complain,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-33" n="33">Such impudence tis, in a Man of his Station,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-34" n="34">To put in one word for the good of the Nation,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-35" n="35">That he with Submission sits silently List'ning,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-36" n="36">Like a Clerk when the Person holds forth at a Christ'ning</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-37" n="37">But ventures at last like a Man of true Sperit</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-38" n="38">To cry, out <hi rend="italics">my Lord, you must know I have merit</hi></l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-39" n="39">Much more than a thousand, and is it not hard,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-40" n="40">That virtue so wondrous shou'd have no reward;</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-41" n="41">But a pitiful Pittance five hundred a year,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-42" n="42">At a time that our very Potatoes are dear</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-43" n="43">My Lord what I tell you is true to a Tittel</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-44" n="44">Or may I be banish'd from licking your Spittle,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-45" n="45">Why then, quoth my Lord, since you give me this Trouble,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-46" n="46">Why then, quoth my Lord, since you give me this Trouble,I tell you, in short you are ev'ry Way double</l>;<l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-47" n="47">As Poet as Docter, as Rector, as Vicar;</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-48" n="48">As dealer, as builder, as planter, as quicker,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-49" n="49">But if you've a mind to be triple, rely on,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-50" n="50">My Word and I'll make you a second <hi rend="italics">Geryon</hi>,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-51" n="51">Ye Critick malicious now read what he says,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-52" n="52">In those Matchless verses on Farmanagh Ways,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-53" n="53">Where all the rough pebles are polish'd so fine,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-54" n="54">Like Emralds they sparkle, like Diamonds they shine,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-55" n="55">Whoever hereafter that fall on these stones</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-56" n="56">Shall think it an honour to break half his bones;</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-57" n="57">Now see the finess of a true politician,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-58" n="58">He'd change for the worse and he'd thrash like a Priscian,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-59" n="59">From thumping the Cushion to make those that Nod.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-60" n="60">Instead of a Sermon he'd brandish a Rod.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-61" n="61">But Charly (tho' Charly) is not such a Tool,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-62" n="62">To Change for more trouble a sine-cure School.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-63" n="63">Four hundred perannum not one Shilling under,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-64" n="64">To preach in two Churches twelve long Miles a sunder.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-65" n="65">And wade it a horse-back in dirt to the knee,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-66" n="66">When Paddy can better wade thro' it than he.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-67" n="67">Observe his address with what artful Submission,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-68" n="68">He tells his rich patron, his grievous condition.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-69" n="69">Quite ruin'd, and bankrupt reduc'd to a farthing,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-70" n="70">By making too much of a very small garden.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-71" n="71">By squand'ring his Mony in Dribs to the poor,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-72" n="72">He's ready to leave the key under the door.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-73" n="73">And grieves that his patron has so much to give,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-74" n="74">While he (more's the pitty is shifting to live.)</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-75" n="75">Again he sollicits in manner most nice,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-76" n="76">By another more subtle and cunning device,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-77" n="77">Because he has hear'd that his patron's well read,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-78" n="78">He layes by his belly and begs for his head;</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-79" n="79">For writing three Ridles had cost him such pains,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-80" n="80">That he scarce has remaing three scruples of brains.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-81" n="81">For want of some Mony he's quite off the hooks,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-82" n="82">To pay off old scores and to buy him new books.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-83" n="83">To re-build a house that he pull'd down already,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-84" n="84">And to buy a fine Ribband to give a fine Lady.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-85" n="85">These are but a few, that I chose from the rest,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-86" n="86">Tho' not one thought in it but can stand the test.</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-87" n="87">Nay more I will venture to swear it surpasses,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-88" n="88">All poems that ever were katch'd at Parnassus,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-89" n="89">Ev'n Horace to Cesar, to this is but barely,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-90" n="90">A thing call'd a poem and Swift to is Harley</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-91" n="91">That poem so valu'd, so often read over,</l><l xml:id="swift-S175A246-line-92" n="92">While Patt's is a reading now sleeps in it's covers.</l></lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
