<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A full and true Vindication of Sir Thom. P────<lb/>  from the many scandalous Libels lately written<lb/>  against him, with the Resolutions of the House.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="JW 14FE09"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="Z712364H">
          <head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-1">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">By a Member of the House of Commons.&#13;</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-2">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">·········───────────────────────────────Nos<lb/>Defendit numerus junctæq; umbone Phalanges. Iuv.</l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-3">
            <lg n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote">
              <l n="1" xml:id="spp-Z712364H-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"></l>
            </lg>
          </head>
          <lg n="1">
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-1" n="1">Ye Dealers in Doggrel, and Friends to the Dean,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-2" n="2">Who dare the Transactions of Senates arraign,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-3" n="3">And give to our Men of Distinction no Quarter</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-4" n="4">From the Knights of the Post to the Knights of the Garter.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-5" n="5">How false are your Libels! How weak is your Spight,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-6" n="6">To rail at Sir Thomas that worshipful Wight,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-7" n="7">Sir Thomas of peerless, Sir Thomas the True-Son,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-8" n="8">That Bulwark and Propp of the Grand Revolution!</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-9" n="9">You call him the Spawn of a Traytor and Felon,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-10" n="10">A Vermin rais'd up from the \<hi rend="italics">del</hi>·Dirt\ Dung, like a Melon:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-11" n="11">You swear, that his Father had no more Religion</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-12" n="12">Than the Ass of Old Balaam, or Mahomet's Pidge\<hi rend="italics">damage</hi>\n.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-13" n="13">That so he escap'd but the Rope, and got Prog,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-14" n="14">Whoever was Miller, he would be his Dog;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-15" n="15">And what he perform'd for our Glorious Defender,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-16" n="16">He would do as well for a Popish Pretender.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-17" n="17">This stupid old Maxim in short you would add,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-18" n="18">“The Treason was good, but the Traytor was bad:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-19" n="19">Which plainly discovers the Cause of your Hate,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-20" n="20">And proves You all Traytors, and Foes to the State.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-21" n="21">\<hi rend="italics">hole</hi>\ Treason you fairly allow to be good:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-22" n="22">(I hope Information is here understood)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-23" n="23">But then the Informer (for Traytor's a Term</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-24" n="24">Of doubtful Construction) was bad you affirm:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-25" n="25">If so, your false Logic we quickly detect,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-26" n="26">“The Cause being nobler than any Effect;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-27" n="27">Nor was he a Traytor, who brought to their End,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-28" n="28">Such Rebels as Fenwick, and Perkins and Friend.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-29" n="29">If he was a Traytor, it must be a Myst'ry,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-30" n="30">It never could be── See Burnet's own Hist'ry:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-31" n="31">'Twas Loyalty made him discover the Plot,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-32" n="32">Not the Neck, that he sav'd, nor the Fortune he got.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-33" n="33">You give out in Speeches, and fain wou'd enlarge on't,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-34" n="34">He was an old Jacobite, Vagabond Serjeant,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-35" n="35">Or Corporal rather── but Sarum has told</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-36" n="36">For certain, that he was an Officer bold;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-37" n="37">And we from the Orthodox Prelate deceas'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-38" n="38">Judge, he was a Major, or Captain at least</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-39" n="39">Our Knight by the Dam-side, you trace but of Blood-low,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-40" n="40">And call the Defendant of King-killing Ludlow</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-41" n="41">And what must become at this Rate of all true Hearts,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-42" n="42">Who bravely brought under the Pride of the Stuarts?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-43" n="43">Our dear Brother Protestants, on whom they droll,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-44" n="44">(I mean the Disciples of goodly St. Noll)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-45" n="45">With very good Reason may sell their Debentures</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-46" n="46">And go to America for new Adventures;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-47" n="47">To avoid cursed Tythes, remove all their Chattels,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-48" n="48">And leave us in God's Name to fight our own Battles.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-49" n="49">You trump up his Grandsire, and gladly would \<hi rend="italics">del</hi>·tell·<hi rend="italics">ins</hi>·dwell\</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-50" n="50">On something, that happen'd some Time at Clonmell:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-51" n="51">You write with ill-Nature, that he among Rogues</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-52" n="52">Convicted, had like to have dy'd in his Brogues.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-53" n="53">That he was a Worthy I grant you indeed,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-54" n="54">Whose gallant Atchievements on Record we read:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-55" n="55">Some make him a Briton, and some a Milesian,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-56" n="56">But I would derive him from Ajax the Grecian:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-57" n="57">Great Ajax, who caus'd many Widows to weep,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-58" n="58">And gave in his Anger no Quarter to Sheep!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-59" n="59">Or, Jason, that travelling Captain of Greece,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-60" n="60">So cry'd up by Poets for bearing the Fleece;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-61" n="61">But Jason however renown'd for his Plunder,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-62" n="62">With humble Submission to him must knock under.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-63" n="63">That Captain one Fleece in his Life only bore,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-64" n="64">Our Hero in one Night would bear off a Score;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-65" n="65">Not such, as the Argonaut's was we are told,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-66" n="66">And yet he converted them all into Gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-67" n="67">For, which the King granted him out of his Bounty</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-68" n="68">Pro tempore Use of his House in the County;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-69" n="69">Whence he, like a Roman in Duty strict ty'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-70" n="70">For the Good, but of Moor, of his Country had dy'd;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-71" n="71">Which great Disappointment and high Provocation,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-72" n="72">Was reveng'd by Sir Tom in the third Generation;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-73" n="73">For all thro' his Doings, and not without Cost,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-74" n="74">His Grandson a Seat in the Senate has lost.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-75" n="75">Some People alledge, that Sir Tom, in this sad Age,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-76" n="76">Thus acted, that he might fulfil an old Adage,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-77" n="77">And some \<hi rend="italics">del</hi>·People\ say the Knight's good Intention was double,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-78" n="78">To serve his dear Country, and save him the Trouble.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-79" n="79">You style him a Blockhead among other Slanders,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-80" n="80">But I to confute you, appeal to By-standers,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-81" n="81">With what Oratorial Grace and Energy,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-82" n="82">He honour'd his Father, and humbled the Clergy;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-83" n="83">How grand was his Aspect, his Action how just</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-84" n="84">Before that Assembly of Wise Heads August!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-85" n="85">The Words of sage Nestor, or else Homer lyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-86" n="86">Descended as soft as the Snow from the skies;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-87" n="87">The Words of Sir Thomas, tho' pompous and big,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-88" n="88">Descended as soft as the Snow from his Wig.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-89" n="89">You add, that Dick B────th and he of one Feather</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-90" n="90">Would ruin the Church and the Clergy together;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-91" n="91">Which shews that your Doctrine can ne'er stand the Test</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-92" n="92">And proves it all Heath'nish or Popish at best;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-93" n="93">The Church and the Clergy are Things as remote</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-94" n="94">As Courtier and Patriot, or Gown and lac'd Coat.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-95" n="95">Religion he wishes may daily increase,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-96" n="96">But thinks her at present so much out of Case,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-97" n="97">That as for her Pastors he fairly wou'd quarter'em</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-98" n="98">Since <note place="foot">·The Seed of the Church is the Blood of her Martyrs.</note> Semen Ecclesiæ, sanguis est Martyrum.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-99" n="99">Or grant them united, his Project will hold</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-100" n="100">And still the Church flourish, tho' ever so old,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-101" n="101">While from her own Members her Nurture she draws,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-102" n="102">As Bears in Westphalia by sucking their Paws.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-103" n="103">But lastly to sum up your long Accusation,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-104" n="104">“He votes for the Drovers that eat up the Nation.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-105" n="105">They eat up the Nation! (That Scandal sarcastic</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-106" n="106">Was broach'd by some covetous proud Ecclesiastick)</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-107" n="107">They eat up the Nation who float it with Milk\<hi rend="italics">hole</hi>\</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-108" n="108">And bring us in Brandy, Tea, Claret and Silk!</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-109" n="109">The Drovers are honest Men to all Intents,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-110" n="110">Their Votes they bestow us, and pay us our Rents:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-111" n="111">Sir Thomas loves Mutton and Beef in their Prime,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-112" n="112">And hopes to see nothing, but Stock here in Time.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-113" n="113">The Drovers he stands for, and tells you moreover</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-114" n="114">That old Father Abraham was but a Drover:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-115" n="115">But as for your Rectors, and Bishops, their Masters,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-116" n="116">Those meer allegorical, nominal Pastors,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-117" n="117">He wishes their Drivers to Heav'n wou'd bespeed 'em,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-118" n="118">And deems them a Burthen to true British Freedom.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-119" n="119">Then who would endeavour to render notorious</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-120" n="120">A Knight so undaunted, a Patriot so glorious?</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-121" n="121">Who, Sir, but the vilest of Scriblers, or rather,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-122" n="122">That dreadful Drawcansir, who libel'd his Father?</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-123" n="123"><lb/>But tremble, ye Wretches, for know, that next Session</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-124" n="124">Each Sinner shall pay for his present Transgression.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-125" n="125">To work, when the Serjeant and I set our Enjines,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-126" n="126">Such sage Resolutions shall pass with a Vengeance,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-127" n="127">That you and the Clergy shall all be as mute</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-128" n="128">As Fishes, and <note place="foot">·Nudier Liberide. Erasm.</note> poor as a Church-Mouse to boot.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-129" n="129">The Press shall be bound to such narrow Restriction,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-130" n="130">A Capital Letter shall pass for Conviction.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-131" n="131">If in a whole Poem without Rhyme or Reason</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-132" n="132">One ────── but appear then, it shall be high Treason.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-133" n="133">No Hawker, or Hawkers, shall open their Throats</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-134" n="134">\<hi rend="italics">?</hi>In\ crying of Papers, but Iournals and Votes.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-135" n="135">No Poet or Author shall dare to be witty</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-136" n="136">Unless he be licenc'd first by a Committee.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-137" n="137">Swift shall be debarr'd then from Paper and Ink,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-138" n="138">He shall not have Liberty even to think,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-139" n="139">And if any Person should ever think fit</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-140" n="140">To rail at his Morals, or carp at his Wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-141" n="141">All Members shall hear him, however absurd</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-142" n="142">And no Man once speak in his Favour a Word.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-143" n="143">However for Ends or Amusement some Folks</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-144" n="144">Caress him in private, and smile at his Jokes,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-145" n="145">Each Senator circumspect there shall befoe him,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-146" n="146">Condemn with his Silence, and seem not to k\<hi rend="italics">hole</hi>\.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-147" n="147">Shake Hands with Sir Thomas, shew how he can plod well,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-148" n="148">With a Sneer, and a Shrug, and a Wagg of the Noddle.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-149" n="149">All true loyal Members shall vote for a Tax,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-150" n="150">And Parsons submit to a Modus in Flax;</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-151" n="151">But no sawcy Rector, or Prelate shall sue</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-152" n="152">For Herbage hereafter, in Court, as their Due,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-153" n="153">Unless peradventure they should be inclin'd</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-154" n="154">To take it like Nebuchadnezzar in kind.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-155" n="155">That Error in State, which so long hath prevail'd,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-156" n="156">The Test sacramental shall then be repeal'd.</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-157" n="157">Thus we with our Brethren shall strengthen the Union</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-158" n="158">By sharing <hi rend="italics">All Places</hi> without a Communion.</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-159" n="159">No Merchant or Tradesman shall then demand Payment</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-160" n="160">From Member whatever, for Meat, Drink, or Rayment,</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-161" n="161">Or sue him at Law for't (a Trespass not veni\<hi rend="italics">?</hi>al,\</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-162" n="162">Or murmur, tho' hector'd a\<hi rend="italics">hole</hi>\</l>
            <l rend="indent(1)" xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-163" n="163">These wise Resolutions to keep Men in Awe</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-164" n="164">Maturely consider'd, shall pass into Law:</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-165" n="165">Whoever gainsays them shall then be forthwith</l>
            <l xml:id="swift-Z712364H-line-166" n="166">Like <note place="foot">·Two Printers who were sent to Newgate by the Irish House of Commons for printing a very innocent Paper on Quadrille.</note> Faulkner and Waters committed to <note place="foot">·Tom. Smith, the Keeper of Newgate, a most cruel, barbarous, inhuman, mercenary Wretch.</note> Smith.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
